[ Silence ]
>> All right.
Apologies for the delay.
Welcome to Computer Science
S-75, Building Dynamic Websites.
My name is David.
I'll be your instructor
this summer.
And it's a pretty brief summer.
So we're going to dive right
in tonight to some material,
then we'll take a breathe, look
at the structure of the course,
expectations thereof,
and then conclude
with some additional material.
And along the way,
please interject
with any questions
that you might have.
But first some questions
from me.
So, you go ahead on the internet
on your laptop or desktop.
You pull up your
favorite browser,
you type in www.google.com
and hit enter, what happens?
Let's tell the story and we can
be as high level or low level
as we want and I'll steer
us in both directions.
So you've hit enter,
what happens?
Give me anything you got.
Yeah?
>> Well, first the request
is sent through your modem
to your internet
service provider
to wherever the Google
website is stored
and then the information
is sent back.
>> Oh good, OK.
So that's the whole story.
So that's very good.
Let's tease it apart
a little bit now.
And I'll repeat some of
the answers sometimes
into the microphone so that our
folks who are taking the course
from afar can hear everything.
So your computer makes a request
to your-- through your modem,
goes to your ISP,
reaches google.com servers
and they reply with a response.
So good, now let's dive in
deeper there, and let's focus
on the active hitting enter to
someone want to propose what--
give me just one step, in
more technical detail what
happens next.
And then we'll get to that
same end point eventually.
[ Inaudible Remark ]
Perfect. So we first need to
translate the name of the site,
in this case www.google.com,
into an IP address.
And someone else,
what is an IP address?
Yeah.
>> Well, it identifies
like a server or?
>> OK, good.
So an IP address, it
identifies a server
or computer on the internet.
And an IP address is simply
a number of this form.
Let me go ahead and pull
up a little scratch
pad for notes here.
So, an IP address, as you've
probably seen, is something
of the form w.x.y.z. And
little internet trivia,
each of these placeholders can
be a digit from what to what?
Or number from what to what?
Sure.
>> Zero to 255.
>> Perfect.
Zero to 255.
And there's some restrictions
on what numbers can be where
but essentially you have number
dot number dot number dot
number, and each of those
numbers can be again zero
through 255.
And if we really want to start
pressing deeper here how many
bits is used to represent
an entire IP address
under the schema?
For those familiar
with bits, 32.
So why is that?
Well for those less
familiar, unfamiliar,
if you want to represent
the number zero through 255,
which is a total of 256
numbers, you need 8 bits,
because 2 to the 8th is 256.
But we won't go into too much
detail on along those lines.
But if you've seen that IP
addresses are just 32 bits,
it is because each of these
numbers is 8 bits itself.
So actually, let's go here,
there won't be much math
in this course after the
following sentence really.
But if you have 32 bits,
how many possible IP
addresses are there
for the world's computers?
Yeah.
[ Inaudible Remark ]
So it's 2 to the 32nd
which is roughly?
Those who are good with
math in their heads?
So it's roughly 4 billion.
So that's a lot but these
days most of you have laptops,
most of you have desktops,
most of you have telephones
in your pockets or
iPads or the like.
So there's more and
more devices these days
that are consuming IP addresses.
So if you follow the popular
media of late you'll find
that people have been
freaking out that we're
about to run out
of IP addresses.
But that's because we've
been using version 4
for far too long.
Thankfully, version 6 has
begun to get rolled out
and version 6 will have 128 bit
IP addresses, which is great
because that's 2 to
the 128, which is huge,
barely pronounceable,
but it will also become
a little more complex
to write these things down.
So we can squeeze a few
more years of discussion
out of these addresses
but realize the world
is transitioning.
Now just for the sake of the
experience for those at home.
Let me actually pause
here, just so we can plug
in this recording device so we
can capture to another format.
So let's leave that as a
cliffhanger for just a minute
or two and I'll be right back.
So, where do we leave off?
You'd just hit enter,
we had proposed
that your computer had
translated or needed
to translate the host
name www.google.com
into an IP address and
then we talked for a moment
about various forms
of IP addresses.
So let's now push
a little harder
on how this translation happens.
So Google has a numeric
address of this form.
And as an aside Google actually
has probably a whole bunch
of IP address of that form.
All of which lead to
the same experience
but perhaps different servers.
So how does your
little Mac or PC
or Linux computer know
what the IP address
of www.google.com actually is?
>> It has to do with a domain
name lookup, the DNS servers.
>> OK. Good.
So it has to do with domain
name lookup using a DNS server.
So for those unfamiliar
DNS is Domain Name System.
And this is an infrastructure
on the internet
that pretty much
does exactly that.
It converts domain
names and host names
to IP addresses and vice versa.
And we'll see tonight that it
does a few other things in terms
of helping with rerouting
of email, with validation
of ownership of domains
and the like.
So there are these
servers out there.
Now your computer, your home
probably doesn't have its own
DNS server but probably
Harvard does if you're on campus
or Comcast does or Verizon
or your company does.
Now if you're at a small
college, for instance,
and you're not visiting
google.com
but you're visiting
somerandomwebsite.com,
it's very possible that you are
the first person on that campus
to visit that website ever
or at least in a long time.
So what if you're small little
campus's DNS server has no idea
what this IP address is?
Are you sort of out of luck
because you went to that school
and not one where there's more
people using that websites?
Or equivalently it's kind of
a chicken and the egg problem.
If you're the first person to
ever need to visit that website
and therefore your campus's
DNS server has no idea what
that mapping is, how do
you solve this problem?
Yeah.
[ Inaudible Remark ]
Exactly, so there's a
hierarchy, thankfully,
to the DNS system whereby even
though you might have your own
DNS server on campus or company
but that doesn't necessarily
store all possible domain names
and IP addresses in the world.
In fact, that would be quite
a large database otherwise,
and it's just not
efficient to keep all of them
around if they're
not being accessed
at all or very frequently.
But your ISP knows some
bigger fish and maybe
that bigger fish knows
an even bigger fish
that has its own DNS
servers that might know.
But in the worst, if no one
along this hierarchy knows,
there also exists in the world
what are called root servers
which are spread
out geographically
across the several continents,
and it's those root servers
that essentially know who does
know what the IP address is
of somerandomwebsite.com.
In other words, those
root servers know
who the authority is for
instance for all of the dot coms
in the world or all of the
dot nets or the like so
that you can have
this initial request
from little old your
computer bubble
up to these very high level
servers and then bubble back
down to some authority
who does actually know.
And the reason for that--
that that works is
because when you go
and buy your own domain name,
which is a process we'll discuss
in just a bit, you have to tell
the world what the IP address is
of your DNS server.
So someone has to be informed
proactively once really
and only once when
you buy the domain.
So for now, let's come back
to our story, we've hit enter,
google.com was in
my browser's window,
my computer has somehow
figured out that it is 1.2.3.4
or something like that.
So now my computer puts
together a message to send it
across the internet
to google.com.
What does that message
look like?
Well, in it's simplest
form it's a message
that pretty much
looks like this.
It is literally the word
GET in all caps, a space,
a forward slash, if you're
just requesting the root
of the web server demarked
typically with slash.
And then HTTP slash
version number.
Now in reality there's a few
more headers, so to speak.
HTTP headers that gets
sent from browser to server
and we'll see those in
action in just a bit.
But this message captures
really the most import aspect
of the request.
So your little computer
creates a virtual envelope,
more technically called
a packet of some sort.
Inside of that packet
is a message like this.
I'll put on the front of
that virtual envelope is a
to address namely 1.2.3.4 or
whatever Google's IP address is.
In the return field of this
virtual envelope, you know,
just like you were mailing
something to a human,
there is the return
address who--
which should be whose
IP address, probably?
So your own IP address and
your computer does know
that if you have an
internet connection.
And then your computer sends
it out on the internet.
Now we can dive deeper
and deeper and deeper
but for now assume that your
ISP has what's called a default
gateway, a.k.a router.
And routers are the computers
on the internet that know how
to get data from
point A to point B
or if they don't know
precisely how to go from A to B,
they know whom to
pass it off to,
who can then get it one
step closer to point B.
So in reality a packet, this
virtual envelope might go
from router to router to router
to router, sometimes as many
as many 30 different
routers across the globe
until finally it gets to its
actual destination, google.com.
Google receives this virtual
envelope, sees that it's
for its IP address, opens the
envelope up, sees this message.
google.com server happens to
be running a web server and so
that web server looks for
the file called slash.
Now slash is typically a
synonym for an actual filename
like index.html or
index.php or any number
of other default
standard filenames.
So Google grabs that file from
its hard drive and then puts it
in its own virtual envelope,
flips the two IP addresses,
the from and the
sender, sends it back
to the internet via
these routers.
It arrives on my computer.
I have my computer, unbeknownst
to me, opens this envelope,
sees a whole bunch of
language called HTML,
renders that HTML top to bottom
and I see the search page
for Google's main site.
Yeah?
>> What is the function
of the slash?
So whenever you type
in a URL, you--
there are several
different components to it.
Http typically followed by ://
followed by something like this,
and so this is let's say
a representative URL.
But we can actually tease this
apart into a few components.
This is the protocol or
schema at the beginning.
Even though in a browser we
almost always use http://.
Have folks seen others?
Yeah?
>> HTTPS.
>> HTTPS similar but different
in that it uses cryptography,
a topic we'll come back to.
Yeah?
>> Ftp://.
>> Ftp://, sftp://, webcal://,
some of these are more
standardized than others
but the schema is typically
an indicator to some piece
of software how it should view
the contents at that address.
So what comes after the ://?
You typically have
something called a host name
or subdomain name
followed by the domain name
which in this case
is google.com,
or followed more precisely
by a domain name with a TLD,
top-level domain, a .com, .edu,
.gov, .uk would be the TLD.
And then you have
what we call a path.
And a path specifies
exactly what file
or folder you want to access.
So a single slash means get
me the root of my hard drive
and if you come from
the Windows world,
this is essentially
equivalent to c:
or on a Mac it's
equivalent to that
or on Linux computer
it's equivalent to that.
So that is truly the
root of your hard drive,
the folder in which everything
else on your hard drive lives.
Now, it turns out you--
in a browser these days,
you don't have to
type most of that.
You can omit the HTTP, you
can typically omit the www,
you can omit the slash
and things just work.
Why is that?
Well, for the most part,
it's because browsers have just
gotten a lot more user friendly,
right.
There was a time, a few years
ago where advertisements
in prints and on TV would
actually have http://
but then the world kind
of realized that you know,
anytime you see www something,
it's probably a website
so we started omitting http://.
Now the world has gotten
acclimated to any mention
of .com or .gov so we don't even
really need the www anymore.
And so, whether or not www works
or doesn't work is actually
completely configurable
by the system administrators
of a website.
And in fact, I don't have a sort
of a soapbox to hop on right now
but invariably during
a semester,
I'll come across some
website for which foo.com
or whatever their domain
is .com just doesn't work,
you have to type in
www.something.com
and that's just a foolish
technical design decision
on their part.
We'll talk today about how
you can configure things
to just work.
And it involves a bit of DNS, a
bit of web server configuration
but typically, you
don't see that dead end
because browsers these
days, if you type in foo.com
and hit enter and there is no
foo.com IP address out there,
the browser will presumptuously
or helpfully prepen www
to the start of the address
and then retry that one.
Some browsers, if
you just type foo,
will automatically
try .com, .net,
.gov some of the
most popular ones.
So in short, a lot of
the technical processes
that are happening are
being sort of hidden now
by browser user friendliness
for better or for worse.
So, the story began with
hitting enter, the story ended
with your seeing the
homepage of Google.
Any questions on the
various steps in between,
whether high level or low level?
Right. So that's the story told
from the perspective of a user.
Why don't we tell the story from
the perspective now of someone
who owns a website or
wants to operate a website?
So suppose one of your goals
in this class or some other is
to actually have your
own presence on the web.
When you actually buy
your own domain name
and have your own business
or personal home page
or whatever the case may be,
how do you go about doing that?
You need more than just
a laptop and a browser,
now you need a server
on the internet
because even though every
computer on the internet,
your laptop included,
has an IP address,
it's not necessarily
publicly accessible.
Because even that statement's
a bit of an oversimplification.
You do not necessarily
have a public IP address.
In fact if you go home and you
have internet access at home,
especially wireless, you
probably have a home router
like an Apple AirPort Extreme
or you have a Linksys router
or some device with antennas
that gives you wireless
internet access.
But Comcast or Verizon or
whoever you're paying each month
to give you internet access into
the house via your cable modem
or DSL modem which in
turn is probably connected
to that router.
If it's not one in
the same device,
which some of the
ISPs provide these all
in one devices these days, odds
are you have one IP address.
And if you have three
brothers and sisters or parents
or grandkids in the house,
all of you are sharing
that one IP address.
And yet the individual computers
in the home still
need an IP address
so what actually is the
case is that when you're
in a home network, you have a--
what's called generally
a private IP address.
Something of the form--
anyone what a popular
internal IP address is?
[ Inaudible Remark ]
Yeah. Exactly.
Anything in fact starting
with 192.168 dot something
dot something is a private
IP address.
So the folks who invented the
internet along the way decided,
"You know what?
We should probably
have some IP addresses
that should never be given
out so that within a company
or a home or a little
test network,
you can have IP addresses that
are guaranteed not to exist
on the public internet."
So what home routers typically
use is 192.168.0 or .1
and then the last digit can be
again, between zero and 255.
But some exceptions, it
really-- it can't be zero,
can't usually be 255 so
there are some constraints
but it gives you roughly 250
or so possible IP addresses.
If you don't like that,
there's 172.16 dot something
dot something.
There's a few more
constraints on this one,
but then if you really need a
lot of internal IP addresses,
you can have a what's called
a class A private network,
10 dot anything is
a private address.
And this actually gives you
millions of IP addresses
for your home or your
business or your data center.
But in short, any IP
addresses beginning with these
and a few other prefixes
are considered private
but the problem then is that
even if after this class,
you know, HTML and CSS all the
better, you know PHP and SQL
and JavaScript and you create
a website and you run it
on your laptop using software
we'll introduce you to,
a web server called Apache,
no one in the world is going
to be able to visit your website
because your address
probably starts with one
of theses prefixes and your
home router or cable modem
or DSL modem is not going
to let outside random people
into your home network to access
this IP address because frankly,
there's tens of thousands
of people who probably have
that exact same private
IP address
so it's just not
uniquely identifiable.
And because your home router
and your cable modem
is sometimes a firewall
onto itself, this traffic is
not going to get into your home.
So in short, that
won't work but you have
at least two options,
two alternatives.
How can you get your
websites out on the internet?
>> Well, if you're still trying
to leave it on your own network
if you port forward to
your own private IP address
from your public IP address.
>> You can.
Port forwarding.
So let's go there,
for those unfamiliar.
When you use a protocol
like HTTP,
you're actually using other
protocols behind the scenes
and in fact you've probably at
least heard the buzzword TCP/IP,
Transmission Control
Protocol/Internet Protocol.
It's actually two protocols.
Two different standards
or languages, so to speak,
that govern how data can be
transmitted on the internet.
And this is a bit of
an oversimplification,
but for today's purposes assume
that IP, the internet protocol,
is just a set of
conventions that humans came
up with years ago that govern
how you associate numeric
addresses with computers.
So IP address derives
from this protocol.
So IP is just the standard for
assigning computers addresses.
However, just assigning someone
an address doesn't mean you can
get data to that address.
For that you need another
standard, another protocol
and that's typically TCP,
Transmission Control Protocol.
So TCP is the standard that web
browsers and web servers speak
in order to actually
physically move data
or electronically
move data from point A
to point B using the higher
level notion of an IP address
to actually uniquely
identify points A and point B.
So for those who might want to
go further in computer science
and in networking in particular,
there's typically what's
called the TCP/IP stack.
And so there's topics
like there's the
transport layer down here.
There's the IP or
addressing layer here,
there's the application layer.
In short, much of the
internet is the result
of smart people having design
things and then design things
on top of thing on top of things
and so we just typically
oversimplify and say TCP/IP.
So what's the point there?
TCP/IP allows not
just the web to work
but all sorts of applications.
There's the web, there's email,
there's instant messaging,
there's-- I mean what else--
there's things like Spotify,
there's dedicated applications
that are using the internet
but aren't necessarily
inside of a browser.
So a server can actually
do multiple things.
It can receive email
like Gmail can.
It can be a website
and get HTTP traffic.
So a server, because it can do
multiple things, somehow needs
to be able to uniquely
identify the various things
that it can do.
And so the world introduced
this notion of port numbers.
And typically for a web
sever for rather for HTTP,
it uses this protocol TCP
and the world decided some
years ago the number 80 will
arbitrarily but consistently
identify this service.
So if you have a server
and you have a website.
And a website uses,
as you probably know,
HTTP but we'll look at
what that means in a bit.
It is running, so to
speak, on port 80.
It is listening, so
to speak, on port 80.
And the motivation for that is
because you might also
have an email server
on the same physical box, right?
Gmail, it's kind of
an oversimplification
but they are both a website
and an email service.
And if you want to be able
to send email to Gmail,
you can also use TCP but
you have to use port 25.
In other words, if you go
to Gmail.com with a browser,
you obviously want
a webpage back.
So even though you, the
human haven't typed 80,
it's automatically
inserted for you
by your browser behind
the scenes.
But if you sent an email from
Eudora or Apple Mail or Outlook,
or whatever you're using,
you again probably don't have
to care about this detail
but that program is going
to send data still to Gmail.com
but specifically to port 25.
So when a computer is on
the internet, a server
and it's listening for traffic,
all of that traffic comes
in on a specific port,
a specific like pathway
into the server so that it knows
if it's a webpage
or an email, right?
Because especially email.
Emails can contain HTML
now so you need some way
of distinguishing the
two fundamentally.
So when you proposed port
forwarding, what does this mean?
Well, if your home network
has a public IP address
and you usually, again,
get one from your ISP,
and that is some address of
the form, w.x.y.z, and you,
your individual laptop on
which you've created your final
project that you want to
make publicly available,
is that one of these
IP addresses,
doesn't really matter
what it is.
What you can do is
configure your home router,
a.k.a. firewall, a.k.a. cable
modem, it depends on what make
and model you have but that
device, you can configure it
to say, any internet traffic
that comes from the internet
to my home on my public
IP address destined
for port 80 should
be "port forwarded"
to IP address 192.168
dot something port 80.
In other words, you
can tell this machine
to take incoming
data on that port
and then route it very
specifically to this computer,
yours, so that it just works.
Now there is one gotcha here,
especially if you have siblings
for instance or other
technically minded family
members or roommates.
If you're doing port
forwarding in this way,
only one of you can operate
a web server behind your
cable model.
Because you only
have one IP address
to uniquely identify
your website
and if you've already
claimed 80 as your own
and that's the default for
the world's browsers to use,
pretty much only your web
server can be accessed.
Now there is a work around here.
If your roommate is really
ticked off at you, you can say,
"Fine, fine, fine, I
will give you port 81."
But what does that mean, that
means the entire world has
to type out a URL like let's
say your address was indeed,
w.x.y.z this would be
your address, your URL.
Your roommate's, unfortunately,
would be this crazy
looking thing.
Right? Or any number
other-- any number really.
Now there are some
restrictions on the numbers.
You just probably can't use
81, but the point is the same.
This is not standard and you
probably don't want your users
having to remember
such an esoteric detail
as an arbitrary number.
However, if on the internet you
visit any website with colon 80,
odds are you will
get to the website
with which you're familiar.
It's just the browser is again
for user convenience inserting
the port number automatically
for you.
And little trivia for HTTPS,
the secure version of HTTP,
what port number does that use?
>> 443.
>> 443. And you sometimes
do see that in URL.
You also see some other
ports commonly like 8080.
8080 is just kind of an
arbitrary popular port
that some company has used
to run certain services.
But in short, using anything
nonstandard these days
especially for commercial
production websites
where you're trying to
make money or trying
to stay online 100% of the time,
using nonstandard ports is bad.
Because there are
certain companies,
there are certain campuses
that will pretty much block
any port besides 80 and 443.
But thankfully there's
a work around.
Even if you want to
run some random server
like a BitTorrent server
or something like that,
all you have to do is change
the port number to be 80 or 443.
So the reality is
with firewalling,
and we'll have this conversation
toward the end of the semester
when we talk about
security more generally,
and a lot of security
mechanisms are kind of a joke
because all you need is a
modicum of savvy or, you know,
having listened to the
past 30 seconds of words
that I just said and you
can circumvent these kinds
of restrictions.
Hotels do this a lot,
Starbucks does this a lot.
But port numbers are really
just this very basic mechanism
and the world has
adopted some standards.
All right.
So, perfect, we have a solution.
All you have to do is
somehow figure out how
to download the manual for your
Linksys router or Apple AirPort
and you can configure all
this port forwarding stuff
and run a website
from your home.
So not quite, right?
Because if you actually have
a popular website, Verizon
and Comcast might
very well notice
and just shut you off entirely
because that huge disclosure
agreement you probably clicked
through and never read
when you've signed
up for internet service probably
said you may not run a website
on your home computer.
So plus this was a pain
in the neck to do anyway.
So we might-- plus I
unplug my laptop sometimes
and so my website is going to go
down anytime I go to-- go out.
So not the best solution
even if you have a desktop.
So let's at least try to push
a little harder and assume
that we need to outsource this
problem or we at least need
to put a computer on
the internet itself
in a data center, on a campus
where it can stay plugged
in perpetually under
your desk at work,
if the sys admins allow it.
And moreover, I don't want
my website to live at w.x.y.z
or any number for that matter.
I want it to live it, david.com
or some URL that is sort
of distinctly my
brand or my name.
So, that begs the
question, how do you go
about getting your
own domain name.
Has anyone done this before?
Yeah, how do you it?
>> I purchase them.
>> OK. Where do you
purchase them?
>> I got mine in Namecheap.
>> OK so Namecheap.com
is a very popular place,
fairly inexpensive.
GoDaddy is another
very popular place.
This one is kind of riddled
with upsell attempts,
trying to get you to buy
everything in the kitchen sink.
But you don't need to do that.
There's all sorts of domain name
registrars out there these days.
Many-- A bunch of years ago,
Network Solutions
was the only one.
But then a market was
created and so there's lots
of places to buy domain names.
For the most part
it doesn't matter
where you buy your
domain name from.
But you do sometimes
get different features.
In particular, you get DNS
feature sometimes, more control
over your DNS servers.
They might throw in free
email accounts, free hosting
but for the most part it
doesn't matter huge amount,
in particular you don't
need to go to someone
like Network Solutions and pay
$30 a year when you could go
to someone like GoDaddy
and pay 9.99 a year
or Namecheap and
pay 4.99 a year.
So in short, just paying more
for a domain name isn't
necessarily giving you anything
more in the way of
functionality.
It depends on what
maybe the add-ons are.
So, how do we go
about doing this?
Well, let's go to
something like GoDaddy.
GoDaddy is kind of a-- Well,
let's actually try Namecheap.
Let's go to Namecheap and
see what they look like.
Namecheap.
Bunch of my friends have
indeed used these websites.
All right.
So let's see, domain
name to search.
I'm going to search for
david.com, probably taken.
Oh, that is a good price.
We're already doing
better than GoDaddy.
All right, so as I
expected, it is taken,
as are almost all
forms of David.
They've suggested I name
myself David John, David Smith,
David Johnson, King David,
David photography dot US.
So, one of the hardest
things frankly
of starting a business these
days is finding an available
domain name, let alone your own
personal vanity domain names
for people's names.
But if we found something
we liked,
maybe I do want DavidTV
dot-- well, that's atrocious,
$6000 for this domain
but if it's not
yet taken it's probably one
of the cheaper ones up above.
So let's assume we found
something we're happy with.
So we add it to our
cart and we check out.
I now own some domain name,
David something dot com.
So what now do I do with it?
How do I associate it with my
web server, and for that matter,
how do we get a web server?
Let's assume I have a web
server and we'll cross
that bridge in a moment.
But I have a domain name,
what do I need to do
with it to start using it?
Well, I need to tell the
world what my IP address is.
So I need to somehow tell
the world that my server,
I don't know who's
going to be hosting it
but I know it will
have an IP address
by nature of how the web works.
So let's assume I know
the IP address is going
to be w.x.y.z. I somehow have
to inform the whole world
that david.com's IP
address is w.x.y.z. So one
of the things I'll have to do
at Namecheap.com or GoDaddy
or networksolutions.com is I
tell the registrar not what my
own computer's IP
address will be
but rather what the IP address
of my domain name's
DNS servers will be.
And the convention is
typically that every domain name
in the world should have two DNS
servers, primary and secondary,
so a main one and a backup one.
They can be one in the same but
the world really pushes people
to having at least two for the
sake of uptime and redundancy.
So I need to know not my own
IP address per se but I need
to know the IP address of one
and then a second DNS server.
Now I don't have my own DNS
servers and I don't want
to go have to configure
two more computers
in addition to my web server.
So this is where web
hosting companies come in.
So in addition to
buying the domain name,
I also want to host
my website somewhere
and it could very well be
the same exact company.
It could be GoDaddy, it
could be Namecheap depending
on the service that
they provide.
But we need to have
a web hosting option.
So what's a web host
going to give us?
A web host is going to give us
a hard drive to put my files on,
you know, maybe not
a hard drive per se,
but some illusion
of storage space.
They are going to have their
own connections to the internet,
this web hosting company.
They are hopefully going to
have a pool of IP addresses
so that I can have
at least one of them.
They're also going
to have some RAM.
They're also going to have
technical support staff.
In short, they're going
to have a server and all
of the things necessary to keep
a server alive on the internet.
And hopefully, they're
also going
to have at least two of what?
DNS servers.
So if I decide to
host my website,
let's say DreamHost.com.
This is a very popular
sort of el cheapo kind
of web hosting company that
I've used myself in the past,
it's like 6.95 or 8.95 a
month, so that's pretty good,
but again, you get
what you pay for.
I wouldn't necessarily
build a big business on it.
So for 8.95 a month, I have
the ability to upload my HTML
and CSS files and soon PHP
and JavaScript files
to their server.
Their server has
nearby two DNS servers,
each of which have
their own IP addresses.
So once I know what
DreamHost's IP addresses are
for its name servers, I
tell Namecheap, or GoDaddy
or wherever I bought my
domain name, and that's it.
The only time I have to talk
to my registrar again
most likely is in a year
when they charge me another
5.99 or $99 for my domain name.
Unfortunately, buying, you're
really renting your domain name
from these registrars.
Now, there's a whole bunch
more involved in setting
up of the web server and
getting my files there,
but at least now I've told the
world that if you want to know
where david.com is, ask these
people, these two IP addresses
of the name server, either one.
And those IP-- those DNS
servers should hopefully know.
Why? Because so long as
I keep paying DreamHost
or someone else 8.95 per month,
they will ensure that both
of those DNS servers know what
my own website's IP address is.
And how will they know?
Because of what I'm paying
for is some storage space
and some internet connectivity
on one of their servers.
One of their servers
has an IP address,
so they just tell
their DNS servers
that david.com's IP address
is whatever the IP address is
of the server they've told
me to put my content on.
And we'll actually look
in a little more detail
of what's involved in that.
But any questions?
So, in answer to the
somewhat frequent problem
where a website does work
at www.something.com but not
at something.com, how do
you fix something like that?
There's usually two
pieces to the solution.
One, you have to make sure
that there's a DNS record
for something.com, that is
there's an IP address associated
with it in addition to
one being associated
with www.something.com and you
need to configure the web server
to accept requests for
either something.com
or www.something.com.
But really, let's focus on
just this DNSPs for now.
So DNS. Turns out DNS is
relatively straightforward,
and once you start operating
a whole bunch of services
on your own website, maybe
you have an email server,
maybe you want to use hosted
services like Google Calendar,
maybe Google Docs, you
can do things like--
actually for CS-75, for
this course, the TFs
and I use Gmail essentially
to host cs75.net's email.
So that's the website as
we'll-- as I'll soon reveal,
if you haven't pulled
up the website.
And we want to be able to have
an email list so that each
of us can email everyone
else very easily.
So we want email addresses
of the form mailing@cs75.net.
Now, how do we do this?
Well, we could set up a mail
server, we could pay someone
to do this, but an amazing
servers out there is Google Apps
with which some of you might
be familiar, and for small fish
like us, where we only
have a few people on staff,
you can actually have hosted
Gmail, hosted Google Calendar,
hosted Google Documents for
I think 20 or fewer people
for free, and what you do is you
configure your own DNS servers
to map something
like mail.cs75.net
to essentially Gmail.com.
So that whenever we send
an email to something
of the form mail.cs75.net,
it figures out via DNS
to actually go to Google.
We could have calendar.cs75.net
and you hit enter,
you actually end up
at Google Calendar,
but our copy of Google Calendar.
And this is all thanks to DNS.
And there's only a few
settings with which you need
to be familiar, and we
already talked about this one.
An NS record is a
record in a DNS server
that tells the world what the
IP address is for that domain.
So, what's inside a DNS server?
Frankly, it's a database
and you can think of it
as like a database with
Excel files, so spreadsheets
that just have rows and columns.
And those columns
essentially represent--
well, in each row
rather, you would have
for instance a domain
name and an IP address.
Domain name, IP address,
domain name, IP address.
That's really all that's
underneath the hood
in a DNS server, at least
so far as we're concerned.
But there are different
types of rows.
So one of those rows can
be an official record
that says the name server, NS,
for this domain is whatever
IP address DreamHost gave me
for instance.
Now, what else can I have?
Well, there's an A record.
So an A record, a row of
type A in the spreadsheet
of sorts is literally
domain name to IP address.
It's as simple as that.
So if I have something.com and
its IP address should be x--
w.x.y.z, that's what's
called an A record.
And I can also have
mail.something.com
or calendar.something.com
and I can associate
with an IP address.
And how do I do this?
It totally depends
on your registrar
or on your DNS provider,
whether it's DreamHost
or GoDaddy or the like.
But these days, it's
usually a web interface.
Back in the day, it
was a command line,
you edit a text file
on a server,
but these days it's been made
to be more user friendly.
But it's essentially
a spreadsheet.
Now, there's two
slightly fancier features.
A CNAME or canonical
name is an alias.
So it turns out with a
lot of these web services
like Google Apps, where Google
is providing the service,
you don't necessarily
want to have
to know what Google's
IP address is, right?
Because one, you probably don't
know anyone who works there,
and so you can't
really ask them.
Now, frankly, you can run a
command and figure it out,
but if you hardcode into your
DNS server the IP address
of google.com, the implication
is that if they ever need
to change their IP address,
which happens, not everyday,
but you know, every few months,
a few years for whatever
technical reasons,
now your website goes down.
It's-- would kind of be better,
at least like it conceptually
if calendar.something.com didn't
resolve to Google's IP address,
but rather, what
if calendar.google.com could
instead resolve more generically
to calendar.google.com.
So don't have your domain
mapped to an IP address,
have your domain name mapped
to someone else's domain name,
and then let their DNS server
tell the world what the current
IP address is of
calendar.google.com.
So in other words, if you want
this layer of abstraction,
where you don't care what the
IP address is, you just care
that your domain
name be a synonym
for someone else's domain name,
then you use a CNAME record.
And what the two columns
look like are domain name,
domain name instead of
domain name, IP address.
So it's a wonderful useful
feature, especially these days,
if you look into
hosted solutions,
not just like Google Apps, but
companies that have services
like customer service forums.
If you go to a website,
they'll often have an address
like support.dell.com or
the like or there's a lot
of companies these days
that provide customer service
websites, but it would look kind
of lame if I go to dell.com
and I get redirected
to customerservice.com.
Dell would rather rebrand
someone else's service to look
like Dell even though
someone else implemented it
and is hosting it.
So via a CNAME, someone
like Dell could say
support.dell.com should actually
resolve to customerservice.com,
but the user should never know
that because the URL
stays support.dell.com.
So that's just one of
the things you can do
with these things called CNAMEs.
And lastly, an MX record
is a mail exchange record.
And a mail exchange record
simply states what is the IP
address of the server or servers
that should handle inbound
mail for this domain name.
And this is great, because
when you use Eudora or Gmail
or Outlook and you type in
deardavidmalin@harvard.edu
and hit enter, similarly there,
you have no idea what
Harvard's IP address is,
but your computer does,
but it's not the IP address
of harvard.edu per se that
your email client needs,
it's the IP address of Harvard's
mail server, so thanks to DNS,
your Mac or PC can ask your
ISP's DNS server or dot dot dot,
this whole hierarchy
we discussed earlier,
can say what is the MX
record for harvard.edu.
And harvard.edu's domain's name
server should be able to say
"send all mail to
this IP address."
And what's nice about MX records
is you can have multiple ones
with priorities, so
websites or rather domains
that have very large
numbers of users
where you really don't want
their mail servers going down,
you can have 2 or 3 or 10
different mail servers,
and the DNS system will say,
try this one, then this one,
then this one, then this one,
just in case any of
those go offline.
And it's all thanks to DNS.
And while we sort of take
all of these for granted,
once you start developing
your own websites,
maybe creating your own
companies or contributing back
to your own school, having
these abilities is wonderfully
powerful, and it really
boils down to these basics.
Any questions?
No? All right.
So that was kind of long.
Why don't we take a three
or so minute break here?
There's restrooms in the
hallway, there's soda machines,
I think, around the whole
corner, and we'll rejoin
in about three minutes.
All right.
We are back.
So why don't we take a
look at the course itself
and what you are in for and what
the course's expectations are.
So, in terms of prerequisites,
the official prerequisites
are these.
So multiple years of
programing experience as well
as comfort with HTML and CSS.
So, what is this
mean in real terms?
So, summer school is very short.
It's, just about six weeks
and the course has three
nontrivially sized projects
and the goal really is to
make sure that at the end
of the short semester, you feel
quite comfortable going off
and doing much more
on your own in the way
of web site development not
just HTML and CSS in the form
of static websites but truly the
dynamic websites that are driven
by a language like PHP and
JavaScript back to the database
like MySQL so it's a
fairly intense course.
If you've only taken something
like computer science S1,
the introductory computer
science class or just one
or two courses, I will
say from past experience,
you'll probably find the course
challenging to say the least
and typically will you estimate
about 30 hours per projects.
So, there's three projects
so you have roughly nine
days for each of them.
It's about 30 hours each
but that was beyond average
so student for whom programming
is a little less familiar
or it's been a bunch of
years since you programmed
or you've only taken one
or two introductory courses
but don't really think of
yourself as a programmer,
the course is definitely
more challenging.
So, do be aware diving in.
I will say if you're on
that fence and not sure
if you're comfort level
and background is there,
you can go to CS75.tv which
is the open courseware site
for the course or we have
several previous semesters worth
of lecture videos,
hand outs, projects,
some of which will be similar
to the summers so by looking
to the past, you
can perhaps infer
as to what the summer will
be like and get a sense then
if the PDFs of past year's
projects completely overwhelm
you or completely excite
you so I would try to use
that as an additional input
tonight before deciding whether
this is the course for you.
In terms of expectations
there are these three projects
in attending or watching, if
distant or unable to make it
in person the lectures,
the lectures will be
structured as follows.
So, tonight our focus
is on HTTP and sort
of the mechanics the underlying
fundamentals of the internet
that for years you've
probably taken for granted
but once you really start
building your own websites
and having to negotiate things
like configurations of servers
and code and databases, tonight
we'll start looking at some
of those more technical details.
On Wednesday and next week,
we'll look at PHP itself.
So, one of the PHPs most
compelling features these days
is one, it's syntactically
very familiar--
very similar to languages
with which many of the folks
in this room and at home
are familiar syntactically,
it's similar to C and C++ and
other procedural languages.
It's very much in
vague, pretty popular,
it's pretty omnipresent
these days in terms
of the web hosting companies
that they're out there
and it's super easy to get set
up even Mac OS comes with PHP
and Apache, the web server pre
installed and there are packages
for Windows and Linux
and other computers
that make it super simple
to get set up in terms
of related languages, Python
and Ruby are probably the two
closest contenders in terms
of popularity with PHP.
And none of this is necessarily
better than the others.
It could vary quickly devolved
into religious debates but one
of the nice things about PHP
is again the omnipresence
of support for it out there
and also I think
pedagogically the documentation
for PHP is outstanding
and as you'll see the PHP.net
online reference manual
for functions and whatnot
is rich with examples,
intelligent discussions
and so we've just found
that it's a very
nice way of diving
in deeper to web programming.
And from a course like this, you
should be able to continue on.
If you haven't come from that
direction already to the likes
of Python and Ruby,
JSP for the JavaWorld,
ASPs for the Windows's world.
There's a lot of
commonalities among them.
We'll transition in lecture
three to looking at XML.
So, when it comes time
to actually stored data whether
statically or dynamically,
you don't need a
full fledge database.
You don't need MYSQL,
you don't need Oracle,
you don't need anything
along those lines,
you could just use text
files but it would be nice
if it's easy to read and
write those text files
so XML is a very popular
language of sort to metalanguage
with which to write
out textual files
and it's representative
more generally
of a topic we'll come back
to in our JavaScript lectures
on the document object model
so they'll be some
commonalities there.
SQL, structured query
language is what's used
by many relational databases
these days among them MYSQL,
Oracle, Postgres and others.
Also in vogue these
days are NoSQL servers,
document storage engines
which we'll look at later
in the semester as well.
But we'll primarily use for
the courses projects MySQL,
we'll look in Lecture
6 and 7 a JavaScript
and it is more general
technique of Ajax,
the ability to use JavaScript
to query a server even
after a page is loaded
to get back more data
for instance Google maps,
does this to get more squares
of mapping information
when you click and drag.
Facebook does this to
push a live updates
from your News Feed
and the like.
We'll look through toward
the end of the semester then
at some higher level
concepts like security
which will interlace
throughout the semester
but we'll really focus on
it in Lecture 8 looking
at common attacks on web
servers, on web sites,
on databases, so as to not
necessarily acquaint you
with everything that
can go wrong but to
at least plant the
seeds in your mind
of things you should
be thinking about.
Indeed there are so
much code out there
that is just vulnerable because
people don't think do things
like sanitize user input
that is they don't check it
for dangerous characters.
So, we'll talk about things
like SQL injection attacks.
We'll talk about a cross-site
scripting attacks and any number
of other ways that are
so darn easy to avoid
yet many people just
don't realize it
or don't know how even though
typically simple little function
calls can fix.
And then the last lecture,
we'll look at scalability.
So, it would be a great
problem to have if you've got
so much traffic that all of the
lessons you learn from lecture 0
through 8 starts-- your website
starts crumbling under the load
and so we'll conclude
the semester by looking
at OK now you have to built
now for a few dozen people,
a few 100 people at your
school but several 1000
or maybe even several 1000
people per second how do you
actually scale from one little
web server to a bigger one
but then once you
have the biggest
and most expensive available
web server what do you do
but you start to scale
as they say horizontally.
So, you get multiple
servers, maybe even cheaper,
slower web servers but
you somehow figure out how
to balance load balance so
to speak traffic across them.
How do you that with databases
how do you that geographically.
How do you do that
with cloud computing.
A buzz word that's all
the rage these days
but has some very interesting
technologies underlying it.
We'll wrap up the
semester looking
at those bigger picture issues.
In addition to set a lectures,
we will have most weeks sections
and office hours so the course
has four teaching fellows,
folks who way either taught
or taken the course before
who'll be with us in the form
of sections and office hours,
sections will be a more slightly
more intimate opportunity
so on Wednesdays and Mondays
typically right after lecture
if you'd like to stick around
to dive a little deeper
into that week's project.
So in addition to the PDF
specification you'll get
of a project.
One of the TFs will walk you
through the week's project
so it give point--
offer some design tips,
some helpful direction,
answer any confusion.
If I do something quite
poorly in lecture,
we can revisit those kinds
of topics and sections
so that you get another
perspective altogether
and then office hours which is
meant to simply follow a section
so one section officially
wraps after an hour.
At office hours will be an
opportunity for one on one Q&A
with one or two of the TFs and
this will be an opportunity
in particular for
questions with the projects
if you're having trouble
understanding something
or trouble chasing down some
bug in addition to reaching
out to us online we'll have
this in person opportunities
for those of who are local, for
those of you who are distant,
more on the online
opportunities in just a moment.
In addition to the courses'
classes, there are projects,
three of them and they will
flow roughly in the order
of the topics on the syllabus
where we'll start in terms
of PHP which would be new to
some or most people in the room,
then we'll introduce
mid-semester databases
and MySQL then we'll introduce
JavaScript and Ajax and so
that all essentially be
the tripartite approach
of the course's projects
in terms of the topics.
In terms of grades, the projects
are graded fairly holistically
because you'll be
encouraged to make a lot
of design decisions on your own.
You won't necessarily have
to implement precisely what we
tell you to rather you'll have
to meet certain feature
in technical requirements
so we'll evaluate the three
projects on this axis.
So, scope will be in axis that
it will be a numeric score
that captures how much of the
project you actually attempted.
Correctness will capture
how much of your code works
in accordance with the
spec. If it's very buggy,
that would now be
considered very correct.
Design is more subjective,
design is OK it might work,
might work perfectly
but does it look
like a mess underneath the hood.
Do you have like 10
nested for loops.
That is not good
design for instance
and so design would
be an opportunity
for particularly
qualitative feedback
from the teaching
fellows on your code.
And style is the more
of the aesthetics
or your variables
reasonably named
or is your code well common?
Is it nicely indented?
The sort of easy things that
are good habits to get into even
if you're not in them that's
what we define a style
and then just for
reference, things are weighted
and roughly the amount
of time that's required
to get things right.
So, for instance this
is the formula we'll use
to compute a total score
for each of the projects,
where correctness for instance
is weighted more heavily
than style and that should
capture the fact that, you know,
indenting your code probably
shouldn't take you all that long
but chasing down bugs can
certainly take quite a bit
of time.
So, the formulas
meant to capture that.
The course's website
which I'll follow
up in just a moment has
everything that you will need
for the course including
videos of lectures
if you can't make some
evening or if it's tricky
because of full time
work, it's totally fine
to watch the course's
lectures online,
of the handouts similarly
will be available there.
What will be rolling out over
e-mail this week is access
to a tool that I actually
we've used in another class
of mine called CS50 but
it's a discussion tool
that will allow you to interact
with classmates, with myself,
with the course's TFs online.
So, online discussion forms
of sorts but using some
of the same technologies
that we'll talk
about in the class
including Ajax and similar.
So, you will soon receiving
e-mails from us with invitations
of sorts to create
accounts within the website
so that we can-- you can
start directing questions
to classmates or privately to
the staff via CS50 discuss.
So, any questions
on the structure,
expectations whether
you're on the right place?
As to the course itself.
No. All right.
In terms of-- yeah.
>> Is there added
credit for attendance?
>> Nope. Attendance is
expected and you encourage
but it's not factored in.
So, see you at the end of the
semester, probably, right?
But in terms of lecture,
typically, we're slated for 3:15
to 6:15, I think, we're
rarely go all three hours.
Typically, the same course
during the year is two hours
of class so we'll typically
have a little bit of wiggle room
and let me not commit to
just two hours per night
but we will typically not go I
think as many as three hours.
So, that's frankly a lot to
take in twice a week, no less.
So, we shall see where
we end up each night.
Any other questions?
With regard to sections, the
implication of that detail is
that sections will
not start necessarily
at the pre-ordained time.
What we'll try to do is the
TFs will come a bit early
so if we're doing the
propping of a lecture,
we'll take a short break then
dive in right immediately
to section in office hours
so that you don't sit here
awkwardly just waiting
for an arbitrary
time to come around.
Yeah.
>> How are we then work
with the distance student?
>> For the distance students,
sections will be filmed as well
and we will be making ample
use of online interactions
for students who are
primarily distance
and we've also experimented in
the past with things like Skype
and video conferencing
or online chats.
We're quite flexible
for whatever works
pedagogically for folks,
>> [Inaudible] distance students
to attend the section
via chat or something?
>> Good question.
Typically, not for distance
students with sections.
We do film them but
there is some latency
and when we post them, we
may experiment with trying
to stream something's online
but this room is not equipped
for that so, I shouldn't make
promises to that just yet.
But either way things will
be available asynchronously
after the fact.
Yeah.
>> What are the office hours?
>> The office hours
will typically be right
after sections on
Mondays and Wednesdays
which are right after lectures.
The motivation being especially
for folks who commute,
we'd figure we try to compact
things to Mondays and Wednesday
so you don't have to
come to campus yet again.
And we're flexible too.
If for instance, you're really
struggling in the class,
you get lots of questions
or your schedule,
you have a night time
class right afterward,
we're happy to do things
by appointment as well.
So, in short, we'll meet
you halfway as best we can.
All right.
So, web hosting companies.
We talked earlier about DNS
and sort of getting traffic
to some destination B
but once they get there,
what's waiting for the user.
Where are your HTML and CSS and
soon, PHP files actually store?
So, this is a little screen shot
from this one company DreamHost
and I don't necessarily
recommend them over any others
but they're popular and
well-known and super cheap.
And just to give you a
sense of what you get
and what you don't really
get, here is a screen shot
of what you get for
apparently for 8.98 per month.
So, you apparently get
unlimited terabytes
of disks storage space.
You get unlimited terabytes
of monthly bandwidth.
You get an unlimited
number of domains hosted,
you get an unlimited number of
user accounts, e-mail accounts,
MySQL databases and a
particular distribution
of Linux called Debian here.
So, it kind of sounds
too good to be true.
So, what is the catch here?
Like that's an amazing
deal for 8.95 a month.
Unlimited everything.
So, what are some of the catches
or what are they doing
here technologically
to make this possible?
>> Well, they're not
alone on their own server.
They're sharing it a
bunch of other sites.
>> Exactly.
So, a lot of these web hosting
companies are shared services
whereby you might get this
but they're also promising
the exact same thing
to 10 other people,
to 100 other people.
Now, it turns out that in HTTP,
the protocol we discussed
earlier,
there is a feature these days
for what's called
virtual hosting.
So, back in the day for the web,
every website needed a unique
IP address, essentially.
So, that when you typed in
something dot com you went
to one website and that
website lived on a server,
that server had an IP address.
And if you wanted
a second website,
you better get a second
server or at least give
that computer a second
IP address.
However, in more
recent versions of HTTP,
we'll see through
some experimentation
with actual browsers, browsers
send another HTTP header.
They don't just send gets.
They also send a
reminder to the web server
as to what the user
typed in to the URL
so that you can now have
these days multiple websites.
Food.com, bar.com, bus.com,
all living on the
same physical server,
at the exact same IP address
and because the browsers remind
the server what the user typed
in, food.com, or, bar.com
or bus.com, the server,
even though its receiving
for three different
websites can figure
out from those so-called headers
what was requested and then,
return the appropriate
domains homepage.
So, in this case, that's great
because it makes this possible.
We only have 4 billion
IP addresses in the world
and they are legitimately
running out and so,
this is great that we can
multiplex servers in this way
and put multiple
people, multiple websites
on the same IP address.
But there's a couple of gotchas,
what's the implication of this,
the fact that multiple customers
are on the same machine?
>> Well, if one-- well if
the server crashes and all
of the websites will go down.
>> Good. So, if the
machine crashes,
now all of you are affected
rather than just the one.
>> Contention for resources.
>> Contention for
resources, right?
So, you're kind of in bad luck--
a bad place, if for instance,
one of the other customers on
the web server is Facebook.com
or something that achieve
unexpected popularity all
of a sudden or maybe it's a
website that's really ticked
someone off and is
getting some kind
of internet biz [phonetic]
attack like a denial
of service attack because people
are going after that website
and just because your server--
your website is on the same
server, now, you are down
or otherwise offline as well.
Moreover, one of the--
one of the ways in which
these companies offer
such discounted prices is
because it's not just you
and two other websites.
It's probably not
10, it could be 100,
it could be 1000 other customers
on the same server and so,
there must be some fine print.
And hopefully, there are
some fine print somewhere
that does say this is subject
to something or rather, right?
They don't have infinite
terabytes on their web server.
bandwidth.
There's got to be some
catch here, otherwise,
the world will not pay
$1000 a month to host
to real large scale websites.
So, you, again, sort of
get what you pay for.
And this is actually expensive.
Years ago, I signed up for
some fly by not operation
for like 2.95 a year to host
my website and it was a website
that I did not care much
for and that was good
because it went down
quite a bit.
So, what they're not
guaranteeing here is unlimited
uptime for instance.
So, there is some gotchas.
But frankly, if you're just
starting small, you just want
to experiment, you need a
place for testing a website
or you don't-- your 8.95 is more
compelling than several $100
or even more, this is
certainly quite compelling.
All right.
But as an aside things
like e-mail and calendar
and whatnot there's
other alternatives.
You don't need to get
those through your web post
when places like Google exist.
But suppose, you are not so
comfortable with that approach
and you suppose too that
you're not comfortable also
with the fact that you
do not have any control
over a DreamHost like server
because it's being shared
by other people and it's
because it's being managed
by other people which is to
say, if they are running PHP 5.2
which is a few years old,
so are you like you
are running PHP 5.2.
And if you want to
take advantage
of new language features that
were introduced in PHP 5.3
and more recently PHP
5.4, you're out of luck
like you're going to have
to other fund a new web
post or just deal with it.
You can't just install
it yourself typically.
So, it's similarly can you
not upgrade different versions
of software.
You can't necessarily
reconfigure the web server
at will.
Now, they might give
you some form of control
but you'll reach a point perhaps
where it's just too
frustrating not
to have administrative
access to the server.
So, you can still achieve that.
So, virtual or private
servers, VPSs or an alternative
to a shared web hosting model.
In the VPS world, you
get a dedicated server
to yourself and sort of.
You get the illusion of a
dedicated server to yourself.
So, thanks to a technology,
generically known
as virtualization, these
days, you can buy a server
with like a bunch of CPUs or a
bunch of course, lots of RAM,
lots of disk space and then, you
can run virtualization software
on it that is something
known generally as hypervisor
like VMware or Parallels
or VirtualBox.
There's a whole bunch of these
products, free and commercial
or like out there that once
you run them and install them
on a server, on top of that
software, you can then,
install multiple instances of
Windows, multiple instances
of Linux, multiple instances,
if they allowed it, of Mac OS.
So you could create the illusion
of multiple distinct
computers each
of which has its own
user names and passwords,
its own administrative or
so-called root account.
And even though, they're
sharing the physical hardware,
they are not sharing
the same software.
So, what you would get as the
customer is the root log in
or the administrator
log in to your machine.
Now, there's still the
risk of resource contention
because these players
too were typically
over provision especially if
you're spending, you know,
9.95 a month and not a 159.95
a month, you're probably going
to be on a server
with fewer resources
or with more customers.
But at least here,
you gain something.
And if you've been
following along,
what is that fundamentally
you're gaining from a VPS
that you didn't get
from a web post?
>> You can choose to update
things, however you wish.
>> Exactly.
>> -- to update.
>> Control.
You can keep things up to date,
you can install whatever
you want and also,
if someone else's server is
compromised odds are your is
might not be whereas
of web hosting server is
compromised everything
on that server is
potentially vulnerable.
So still not perfect
because the reality is
to even know you are the
only one now with root
or administrative access because
it is a dedicated albeit virtual
server for you that
to you is kind
of a white lie who
else has access?
>> The people there.
Even if they don't know your
password they have physical
access to the machine
and as soon as you
as your physical
access to any machine
in the world pretty much
you can compromise it.
You can boot-- you know, Linux
computer for instance can booted
in what's called
single user mode
by pretty much hitting the
letter S when it's booting up
and that circumvents
any request for password
at which point you
can even change it.
Even on PCs and computers
you can usually reset certain
passwords by opening the case up
putting a little metal connector
on two pins and it
short circuits
out the password
and clears it out.
So in short physical
access bad for security
so you're not gaining more
security fundamentally,
you're just making
it less likely
that someone else is
compromised will affect you.
And in some of these
system some software
that system administrators
will have the password
or at least access to the
root account on your server
so in short you should just
assume that this is for you
but it probably at least one
other person could physically
access your contents.
So what do you get though
for the money, well here
and frankly these numbers
are a little more compelling
because is not unlimited
so I'm kind of incline
to believe a bit more
about the quality
of service we're getting here
but 20 gigabytes of storage,
you know, that's fine
for typical website unless your
website has a ridiculous amount
of traffic and database traffic
and logs which could build up
and start taking megs
or gigabytes of space.
Or if you allow users
to upload files
or photos then you might
need a lot of space
but many websites even if
they are dynamic this is
probably plenty.
Transfer is an interesting one,
20, 200 gigabytes per month,
for most websites that's
probably fine unless your
website is photo website
or worst a video website then
you have to start to do the math
and figure out exactly
how much trend--
data will be coming in and
out of your server based
on users patterns and moreover
there's also corner cases
as we'll discuss toward
the end of the semester,
you got to worry about
the bad guys out there.
If someone just doesn't
like you or is bored
or downloads some free piece
of software that bangs up--
bangs the heck out of your
computer they could just eat
up your monthly allotment
of bandwidth just
by sending bogus traffic
or downloading the same video
again and again and again.
So there's very interesting
adversarial tax
when you have finances somehow
tied to usage so you need
to be aware of that
especially with cloud computing.
And let's see you get some
amount of RAM 512 megabytes here
and so forth one of
the things we'll look
at during the semester
is we start playing
with Apache is it will
give you the sense
of how you can asses how much
RAM your computer is using how
much disk space its using.
I dare say one of the
most of common platforms
for web hosting these
days whether it's a VPS
or it is a shared
web post is Linux
in some form whether it's Debian
or Fedora or Ubuntu or Red Hat
or CentOS or any number--
versions of Linux.
We'll happen to use Fedora in
the class but its representative
of many similar operating
systems.
You can use Mac OS but it's
not really use commercially
through host websites just
because is not really
geared toward that.
You can use Windows but you
really-- there's no good reason,
there's no technically
compelling reason
to use a Windows machine to
host things like PHP or Python
or Ruby because you're paying
money for Windows license
to run free software so it's not
necessarily compelling unless
you already have the licenses
and have the machines
generally going
with these open source tools
is quite common and compelling
because none of the
software were used
in the course costs
any money or whatsoever
and it's nonetheless
quite popular and robust.
All right so what
else, the appliance,
so we won't introduce it
tonight but we will in the form
of the first project so that you
have an experience in the class
that is as realistic
as possible.
What we'll actually have each
of you do is run
your own web server
and run your own
data base server
and actually run your
own copy of Linux itself.
For this we'll use another
tool that I used in other class
of mine called the
CS50 Appliance,
and this will be a
downloadable file that inside
of which is an installation
of Linux,
Fedora Linux specifically,
but also installed for you
in advance will be a Apache
which is web server
software MySQL
which is data base software, PHP
as well as support for bunches
of other languages and
standard tools and the like,
and the upside of this is that
rather than have you connect
for instance to some
random Harvard servers
on which you'll only
have temporary access,
this is a virtual machine
that you have on your computer
for as long as you
want to keep it around
and it's very representative
of the configuration.
You would find out of VPS
or the commercial web post.
And because you'll
have root access on it
and because it will be leave
on your machine only you
have perfectly secure access
to it unless your laptop
or desktop is compromised
and you'll be able to configure
Apache and PHP and really tinker
with things and best get--
best yet if screwed it up,
that's fine, just download a new
one and you're back to a sort
of the beginning so long
as you've saved your code
at somewhere which
will encourage you how
and where to do.
So more than that in a week
or so, how would you connect
to this kind of thing, so SSH.
Does anyone use-- Does
anyone not use SSH here?
There is going to be some hands?
OK. So if you haven't used
SSH, stands for secure shell
and this is a way,
sort of old school way
but now a much more secure of
connecting to a remote server
and executing commands on it.
So this is just a free program
that comes with MacOS Terminal
and there is analogs for the
windows or a patti [phonetic].
It's a free program for windows
that a lot of people like to use
and it allows you to open
up essentially a black
and white window or white
and black window and type
in a username and password,
connect to some remote server
and execute commands on it.
And those commands can
be to create files,
remove files configure the
web server, turn the database
on or off for the like.
So what you'll find, once we
start using this CS50 appliance
or virtual machine,
albeit running
on your own computer not some
server is you will be able
to connect to that appliance
as though it's a remote server.
So that you never even need
to see the appliance itself.
Literally, once you turn it on,
you can minimize it and pretend
that it's a server
somewhere else in the internet
because once you install
it, the appliance,
a.k.a. virtual machine is going
to have its own IP address
but it's going to be
what type of IP address?
So it will be private
to your own laptops
and no one else can even access
it but you'll be able to go
through precisely the same
motions that you would
if you're actually paying some
third party to host your website
or if you own some server
else where on the internet.
So SSH will be one of the
techniques that we use.
SFTP for those unfamiliar,
this is screen shot
of a popular windows client
for transferring files,
called secure effects but others
exist, free ones in particular,
it just let's you drag and
drop files from your computer
to a server but in this
case, the server is going
to be a virtual machine
running on your own computer
that maybe-- maybe or
maybe not is minimized.
But again, the experience
would be precisely the same.
So where does that leave us?
So it turns out when
you are writing HTML,
you have fairly static content
but you do have these mechanisms
and I'm guessing most people
in the room have some or a lot
of experience with HTML and
basic websites and the like.
But these ultimately are
the basic input mechanism
by which we can start
making dynamic websites.
In other words, we have text
fields, password fields,
hidden fields, checkboxes,
radio buttons, drop down menus,
so these are the mechanisms by
which we can start to get input
from users so that when they
interact with our website,
they don't necessarily see the
same thing rather they might see
different things every
time we visit that website.
So let's do a little
example here.
I'm going to go ahead and--
don't download this
on your own just
yet because we will be
posting a newer version soon--
but I'm going to go ahead and
open up a program called fusion,
VMWare fusion, this is what's
called generally again a
hypervisor virtualization
software,
and what I've just done
is essentially run Linux
on my own Mac and
you too can do this.
I'm going to actually use
the Linux desktop just
because it's here but I could
similarly minimize it as I will
in just a few minutes and
we'll connect to it as well.
So now, I'm running
Linux on my same computer
and notice I currently
have no IP address
but this should change in a
few seconds once I get a--
there we go.
So my Linux computer virtual
machine has just asked the
network to give me an
IP address and it came.
The protocol that computers used
to get IP addresses
dynamically, does anyone know?
DHCP, Dynamic Host Configuration
Protocol, that's what did that.
It's also how your own
personal computer works at home
and gets an IP address
from your Linksys router
or AirPort Extreme.
So I'm going to go
ahead and do this.
First let me go to
my, back to my Mac.
I'm going to open up the
simplest of programs text edit
which is what we used
earlier and I'm going
to just make a very
simple web page.
First, I'm going
to do DOCTYPE html.
So in the course, we'll use html
5 which is sort of the latest
and greatest version of html
and I'm going to say "Hello."
Well, let's do this.
Let's call this Google and
the body and then close body
and then I'm going to
say Google, h1, OK,
I'm going to save this.
I'm just going to
go ahead and save it
on my desktop as Google.html.
I'm going to say yes use html
even though it's a text file
and now I'm going to go ahead
and pull up Google.html.
OK. So not exactly Google just
yet, I can do a little better
so let's make this
a little different.
So let me go in here, div
style, text-align: center.
So if any of these looks
completely cryptic or new,
these are the kinds of things
that we will take for granted
in the course, that this
stuff looks familiar.
So let me save and reload.
OK. Now, it looks a
little more like Google
but it's certainly lacking in
some key features among them.
All right, search bar, right?
So let's go there.
So let me start to make a simple
webpage that again odds are many
of you could have done
already because you know HTML
and forms and whatnot.
So, let's go ahead and do this.
So down here, I'm
going to say form,
I'm going to close my form,
I'm going to go in here
and I need an input
type equals text
and I probably need
a submit button,
so let me do input
type equal submit
and I'll give this a
value of Google search,
what we really recreated as
best we can, save and reload.
OK. So now, it's getting there.
You know, this isn't
the prettiest thing,
so let me go ahead and do style
with let's say 200 pixels.
Let's go back here and save
and it's still a little
small, 300 pixels.
OK, looks more Google like.
And then if we really want to
be anal here, we could do this.
I'm feeling lucky, OK.
So now we've got roughly
Google but in black in white.
So unfortunately, it
takes way more work
to implement the
backend of this website.
Right? So front end,
pretty easy.
We're pretty much done
other than some colors
and some other features
these days.
But what about the backend?
So if I actually wanted
to patch in to Google,
let's see if we can now revisit
that conversation
we started earlier.
When I type www.google.com
and hit enter,
what really is happening?
Let's take a look
underneath the hood.
Let's look at the
HTTP traffic and think
about what it is we're going
to start building next week
in terms of the actual backend.
So let's suspend
this mental thread,
pull up the actual google.com
and take a look at what is here.
I'm going to ahead first so
that this is enlightening.
They hid it so we have
to disable this annoying
instant search feature.
Let's select this.
Gear icon, search settings,
Google instants, how
do I disable you.
Never show instant results.
So the reason I want to do
this is we're not going to talk
about JavaScript and
AJAX, the technologies
that underlie this annoying
or beneficial instant
search feature.
We want to do sort of old
school HTTP searches right now.
So I've disabled that.
So now hopefully, I can save.
OK. Now, I'm going to
go back to google.com
and this is what it was like
five years ago when you wanted
to search for something
on the internet.
So now, I'm going to go ahead
and type for instance Harvard.
So it's still doing
auto complete
but it's not immediately
showing me the search results.
So now, notice before, here
is URL I'm at, www.google.com.
And now after, let me hit
enter, now notice the URL.
So this is now hinting
at the fundamental
functionality of HTTP.
We have just issued one
of those get requests.
We had two of them in fact.
The first one came up when I
visited the homepage then I hit
enter and it appears
that another get
request has been sent.
Why? Because my URL changed.
So generally, anytime the
keyword get is involved,
it's because the URL is
changing or equivalently
if the URL changes, you
just did a get most likely.
So there is a whole lot of
distracting stuff up there
but what is relevant
and what looks familiar
up there in the URL in gray?
I have no idea what HL is.
Sites, I don't know.
Source, I don't know.
But what looks familiar?
OK. Harvard.
So let me delete
manually all the stuff
that I have no idea what
it means, at least not yet.
So let me, I don't
know what this is.
Q equals Harvard that I--
oq equals Harvard,
oq, I don't know.
I'm just going to presumptuously
whittle it down to that
and now let's hit enter.
So interestingly, still
works and what's nice is
that there is much
less distraction
and we can have the same story
but with fewer distractions
in the tail.
So it looks like when hitting
enter on the previous page,
if I throw away the
distractions,
I have now visited, not
slash but slash search,
question mark, q equals Harvard.
So what is q?
Q is generally known
as an HTTP parameter.
So it is an input
to a web server
that generally comes
from a form.
But as we'll see in a few weeks,
it can also come
from JavaScript code.
It doesn't have to come
from a form per se.
Harvard is obviously
what I typed in.
So what is slash search?
Well, it's not obvious here what
programming language Google uses
but if we were on Facebook, we
would probably see search.php
because Facebook is
known for using PHP.
They're also known for not
hiding their file extensions,
which is very easy to do but
they just don't for some reason.
Google does hide their
file extension but a lot
of Google's code, at least
front end is written apparently
in Python or in some
other languages.
So it's not clear what
language is on the server
but slash search is
referring to some file
or some folder on the server.
What does the question
mark denote?
What's that?
>> Start.
>> The start of the parameters.
So anytime you have a
question mark in the URL,
that demarks the path and
the preceding part of the URL
from all of the parameters and
parameters are key value pairs,
something equals something.
And if you have multiple
parameters, what separates them,
even though I already
deleted the others.
Yeah?
>> And.
>> The and, the ampersand
symbol.
So if I hadn't deleted
all of that,
recall that we saw something
like this just a moment ago
and oq equals Harvard.
And I don't know what oq is
but that's how you would
separate parameters,
with ampersands.
So this means we have
submitted key of q and a value
of Harvard to the server.
So now, let's use a fairly
common tool built into Chrome.
It's also built into Safari.
Firefox has something similar
when we recommend
something called Firebug
on the course's website
with which
to do the same kind of thing.
But I'm going to go to View,
Developer, and Developer Tools.
And I will say these days
certainly when using LAMP,
Linux, Apache, MySQL and PHP,
which is this course's focus,
many people are increasingly
using Chrome, one,
because it's popular, two,
because it's fast, three,
because it comes with
some developer tools.
I would say Firefox is
also wonderfully convenient
for doing development and
you should certainly test
on multiple browsers as
we'll require in one of the--
in the first project
spec. You can do Window--
rather Internet Explorer
is getting better
about having some
integrated development tools.
From the courses perspective, we
don't care about browser you use
because you'll be using again
the appliance as a server.
You can use whatever browser,
whatever operating system
on your own computer that
you're most comfortable with.
But if you are coming
to this with some,
I'd say less familiarity
with various tools,
Chrome is pretty popular
and Firefox tend to be,
I think better for development
purposes even though you should
test on all of them.
So what am I seeing here?
I've just opened the developer
tabs, and now I have elements,
resources, networks,
scripts, timeline,
profiles, audits and console.
We're not going to use
all of these but a few
of them are quite helpful, one,
the elements tab shows
you the pages HTML
but it pretty-prints it for you
and it makes it hierarchical
so that with those little
triangles, you can dive
in deeper and see even though
if we look at view source
for the page, it is an
utter mess of a page.
If I go over here
and view page source,
this is what came
back from the server.
And I would argue this is
not very readable to a human,
even when we get
to the actual HTML,
even the HTML not that readable.
Color coded maybe,
still not useful.
So what does this do?
It actually-- The developer
toolbar actually parses it
for you so you can
start to navigate.
And this is actually wonderfully
compelling whether it's your
site or someone else is.
If it's someone else
is, it's a wonderful way
of learning how they
did something
or how they stylize something.
If it's your own site,
it's a wonderful way
of chasing down bugs.
And also as you'll see,
changing on the fly some
of the aesthetics without
having to change actual files
and then reload or re-upload.
So, we don't care so much
about elements right now
but we do care about network.
So let me go to the network tab.
And what this tab will
do for us is sniff all
of the network traffic between
my browser and the server
and it will show each
HTTP request one per line
at the bottom.
So I'm going to leave
this window open,
I'm going to click reload.
And again, this is my URL.
And here we go.
That's a lot.
I only hit reload once
but why in the world
that so many rows
appear down here?
I clicked once, but look how
much stuff just happened.
Why? Each of those again
represents an HTTP request.
So a virtual envelope from
browser to server and back.
Yeah?
>> Well there's a lot
going on behind the scenes.
>> What does that mean,
behind the scenes?
>> Well, Google doesn't just
have one method for [inaudible].
There's things that it has to
call, other things that it has
to find and bring up and so
that's all coming up in this--
>> OK, good.
So Google needs to
pull up other things.
Give me a concrete example of
something it has to pull up.
>> Like an image.
>> Good. So inside of the HTML
that's initially downloaded,
there could be an image tag, a
source tag, a link tag to CSS,
to JavaScript, to images,
it could be flash files,
it could be a whole bunch of
other assets, so to speak.
And to get those, the
browser is predefined to sort
of recursively go
get those assets.
So if it sees a source
tag or an image tag,
it will send another
virtual envelop requesting
that file specifically.
It might do it over the
same network connection,
the same TCP socket,
so to speak,
but each of these rows
represents a different file
that was downloaded.
Ironically, it seems that
Harvard is not behaving well
in the terms of the auto
previews but that's good.
In another day we
can look at why.
But let's look at the first one
because that's the one that'll
be the most enlightening
for now.
And when I click on this,
there's a few detail.
So, one, the preview is
just what was returned.
And here is another big mess
of results from the web server.
But we don't care
so much about that.
I care about the headers.
So let me zoom in on this.
And rather than look at this
fairly pretty-printed version
of it, I want to look
at the raw source.
So, we're diving in deep
sort of intellectually here
so let me look at view source.
Now this is what was literally
sent in that virtual envelope
that we started tonight's
discussion with.
So, there's the top line,
GET/search?q=harvard
HTTP/version number,
so that was in the envelope.
And we did promise there's
some other stuff in there.
Second line is a
reminder to the server
as to what the user typed in.
So what is the host name.
Now frankly Google is
not sharing their servers
with other companies most likely
so this doesn't really
matter there.
But for shared web
posting companies,
the fact that I'm being reminded
what the URL was means I can
serve up foo.com or
bar.com or bus.com,
so thankfully HTTP does that.
There's some arcane information
here related to caching
and connections and efficiency.
Well let me wave my
hand at that for now.
User-Agent is interesting and
you might know this already
but if you don't, every webpage
you've ever visited has--
every website you've ever
visited knows what computer you
have and what operating
system you're running
and what browser you were using.
Why is that?
Well browsers by default reveal
precisely that information.
I have just told
Google, behind the scenes
that I have a Mac running Mac
OS X 10.7.4 and if I scroll
down further, they
will be able to infer
that I was using Chrome
version something or rather.
So why in the world
is that useful?
Yeah?
[ Inaudible Remark ]
Good. So, arguably, this is
useful for debugging purposes,
useful for demographic purposes
to know who your users are.
[ Inaudible Remark ]
Good. So there are some
features that could be dictated
by what type of OS or
browser someone is using.
For instance, if
you go to a website
that lets you download software,
you know, it's not necessary
that you detect what the user's
operating system and browser are
but it's kind of a
nicer user experience
if the server only shows
you the Mac software
because you clearly have a
Mac as opposed to me having
to figure out which
of the links to click
for Linux or Windows or Mac OS.
Another argument frankly is that
this is completely unnecessary
and we should never have gotten
to this habit in
the first place.
Because if for-- it's not
necessarily used all that much.
And indeed, writing websites
that require knowing what
the user's browser is,
is actually generally
bad practice
because there will be
certain privacy tools
that users can install
in their computer
that just hide this
information altogether
for better or for worse.
And if you're relying on
certain headers to be sent,
your own website
could misbehave.
So there are-- it turns
out there's other tricks
for doing detection and
typically as we'll see
in JavaScript, it's
better generally
to detect whether a browser
has a certain feature rather
than is it a specific
operating system
or a specific version
of a browser.
However, databases freely
available exist that allow you
to figure out based on the
so called user agent strings,
what version of browser
and operating system
someone's using.
Because frankly this is
a little hard to read,
so software exist
that simplifies this.
So you can just check a boolean
variable is Mac or in PC.
All right, what's below?
Some more arcane details
that I'll wave my hand at.
Cookies we'll come back
to in a week or two
when we actually start
using them to our advantage
but we'll also talk about the
security implications of them.
But in a nutshell,
all of these headers,
just text is what was inside
of that virtual envelope.
And the most important one
arguably was the very first one
because that tells
Google what to return.
But now we see that it's not
just slash, it's a full path.
So Google has hopefully parsed
that string, so to speak, slash,
search, question mark,
q equals Harvard,
and then use the q equals
Harvard as input to its database
or whatnot to return
customized results to me.
Now if we scroll down, let's
see how Google replied.
So this is just a Chrome thing.
It is just kind of
dumbed down display
of the query string
parameter, so it's just useful.
Especially for a developer you
can just see it more easily
this way.
But let me go ahead and view
source now for response headers.
This is what the
server responded with.
So it turns out many of you have
seen numbers return by server.
Who has ever seen the
message 404 come back?
OK. What does 404 mean?
[ Inaudible Remark ]
File not found, right.
So it's an HTTP status code.
It's an arbitrary number the
world decided on years ago
that means file is not found.
What are some others you might
have seen besides this one?
[ Inaudible Remark ]
501, so internal server
error of some sort.
503, it's another internal
error or resource forbidden.
There's 403 rather
which is forbidden.
What's that?
>> 301 and 302.
>> 301 and 302 are redirects
which are actually quite useful
and we'll start using those
in the next lecture or two.
So in short, there's some codes
that you've probably seen.
404 is maybe the most popular.
200 you might not have ever
seen, but this is the best one
of all, 200 is literally OK, it
means everything worked out well
so you just don't see it
because it indicates success
as this little green icon
that we saw a moment ago
before I expanded this.
So, this is the server's
response, 200 means,
found what you're
looking for, here it is.
Now, what else comes down?
We have the date from the server
which might be useful, expires
and cache control, so directives
to the browser saying, doer,
don't cache this, even though
these are not necessarily
reliable, but we'll talk
about this when we get
to PHP, this is interesting.
Set-Cookie, Set-Cookie is
amazingly powerful, if not,
a little unsettling especially
in the world of advertising
and tracking, but
we'll talk about that
in the context of PHP.
Notice that the server is
telling us that it supports gzip
which is like a compression
utility,
which is a compression utility
and this just means, hey,
you can compress your
data to and from me.
The name of the server, gws,
probably Google web services
and then some headers
that they use for some
of the security things
we'll talk
about later in the semester.
So that's what Google
has returned in addition
to the content that has
come back from the server.
So let's see this outside
the scope of our browser.
I'm going to go on and open
a program called Terminal
which comes with Mac
OS, for those of you
with Windows PuTTY is another
option and we'll look at that
or encourage that in-- my
music is still playing.
We'll look at that,
we'll recommend
that for future project
and I'm going
to run a program called telnet,
telnet is like SSH
but unencrypted.
You know, that's bit of
an over simplification.
I'm going to go head
and telnet to google.com
and nothing actually happens.
But it did figure out
Google's IP address,
so that's interesting.
But telnet by default uses port
20-- it's been so long, 21,
tenet uses port 21, TCP port 21
but there's no telnet server
there, telnet use to be
to send messages and connect
to email serves and the like.
But what if I instead say
80, so there's no colon
in this program, there
is in the browser.
But this is going to
connect from my laptop
to google.com on TCP port 80.
So this is interesting.
Now, I've connected
to their server, why?
Or how do I know that?
It's telling me, connected
to www.l.google.com.
Where did this l come from?
They're doing some DNS
trickery, it's probably
for load balancing purposes,
they have multiple servers,
so therefore, I've gotten
one of them, specifically.
But I'm going to
pretend to be a browser.
I'm going to say, get me
slash using HTTP version 1.1
and then hit enter.
And then if that's the
last of my headers,
I have to hit enter twice,
and viola, what do I see?
Well the font is kind of big
and HTML and Java Script is kind
of minified but that's exactly
what my browser got back.
But if I keep going up
and up and up and up,
notice I can see exactly what
the server's response was.
So I see my HTTP headers that
came back from the server,
Set-Cookie and all
those same lines,
exactly what I saw
on the browser.
So I've just pretended
really to be a browser.
And we can do this with
any websites and it's more
than just a curiosity, it can
actually help with debugging
or actually seeing what's
coming back from a server.
I can do www.harvard.edu 80.
GET/HTTP 1.1, enter, enter.
So, interesting.
Bad request.
Now why is that?
So we see some HTML,
because this--
the web server assumes
that a browser will
typically be doing this.
Why might this be a bad request?
I'm actually going
to guess here.
Let's try this, GET/HTTP
1.1, Host harvard.edu.
There we go.
So it didn't like the fact that
I did not send the host header
which means Harvard's web server
is probably using something
called virtual hosting, which
is that feature I alluded
to earlier when a
website can support--
when a web server can support
multiple websites but for
that to work, browsers
have to cooperate.
And the fact that I did
not send that header meant
that the server didn't know
who's home page to return
so it gave me that 400 response
of I don't know what to do.
Now let's try one other
thing, let me cancel this
and let me do, telnet
to not www.harvard.edu,
let's try this one,
just see what happens.
So GET/HTTP 1.1, enter, enter.
OK. It didn't like that.
So let's fix this again.
So, GET/HTTP 1.1, Host
harvard.edu, enter, enter.
Interesting.
This is not the home page?
What did I get this time?
Some message about it's moved,
harvard.edu has moved
permanently no less.
And if I scroll up,
more esoterically
in the headers is one,
a different status code,
301 which we mentioned earlier,
301 means permanent redirect.
If a browser receives a 301,
it should never ask
that question again.
It should just remember
harvard.edu moved,
and it moved where?
To the value of the
location field
which should also be included
in the response headers.
How did that happened?
Well some system
administrator or a dean
at Harvard just decided
arbitrarily that's--
but reasonably, that we
don't want to standardize
on harvard.edu in our
browsers and people's browsers.
We want them automatically to be
redirected to www.hardvard.edu.
Why? One, branding, I
mean, that's one reason,
which is perfectly reasonable.
Two, more technologically,
it can be better for,
security is a bit
of an overstatement,
but for technical reasons,
having the www means your
cookies can be isolated
to www.harvard.edu, whereas, if
your cookies were instead sent
to hardvard.edu, that means your
cookies could be read really
by any websites, so
including cs.harvard.edu
or summer.harvard.edu.
So by saying www, you're
also forcing at least
by default cookies to be
more precisely defined.
So there are some
technical reasons as well.
Only a year or two was
this problem fixed, they--
few years back, someone
new came to Harvard
to run the news office and
one of her first things,
one of her first acts was to fix
a horrific omission for years
where harvard.edu did not exist.
www.hardvard.edu existed and
they weren't even redirecting.
So, that is a bug
that's now been solved.
Any questions then on
what just happened there?
You all have the terminal
window open, let me offer
up some other troubleshooting
tips.
NS look up, name server
look up is a wonderful way
of doing those DNS look
ups we talked about before.
What I've just done is ask the
nearest DNS server which happens
to be this because that's how
Harvard has configured the
campus, that's the DNS server.
And I've asked what the
IP address of hardvard.edu
and it's given me
this IP address.
So if I want to get
curious, let me do this,
http://ipaddress, interesting.
Why this is not working?
Well, again, VHosting.
Like the website
is not configured
to understand IP
addresses by default.
However, let's try another one.
NS look up cnn.com-- oops,
cnn.com, well interesting.
So it turns out with DNS,
you can also do what's
called round robin.
You can return multiple IP
addresses for a web server
and those can rotate
literally in the order
in which they're returned to do
load balancing and we'll discuss
that topic again toward the end
of the semester in scalability.
But let me choose one of these.
And CNN either pretty big.
I am guessing they don't
really share with some other
with some other websites.
So let's just go
their IP address
and indeed, there it works.
And now notice my
URL hasn't changed.
So now, if I really
want to get sort of--
if I really want to get sort of
creative, I'm going to do this.
On my Mac and you can do this
on a Windows machine as well.
There's typically a file on
Macs and Linux computers,
it' called etc host which
a text file that maps,
that hard codes IP
addresses for domain names.
This is useful generally
for internal corporate use
or development purposes.
So we'll be able to do
this with projects as well.
I'm going to go ahead
and authenticate here.
It's just a text file and
notice this is some basic ones
that come with the system.
This is an IPV 6, version 6
address written in a crazy from.
I'm going to go ahead
and paste in not the URL
but the IP address
of CNN and I'm going
to say this is davidnews.com.
So this is like manually
overwriting,
the mapping of that IP
address to something else here,
only from my own computer.
I'm not running a DNS server.
It's just that my
Operating System Mac OS
and Windows is supposed
to look at a file
like this before
asking a DNS server.
So now let's see if this works.
It doesn't work with all
websites but let me go
to http://dividnews.com.
Come on. Oh, come on.
There it is.
I've just made my own news site.
So, frankly, this is
kind of stupid of them.
Like, I was just joking with
some friend the other day
that you could kind
of have fun with this
and make fairly offensive
domain names
and they all lead
to CNN somehow.
And why is this?
So, this is trivial defects
frankly in a web server.
A web server could be configured
as you will be able to do
with features of Apache before
long of checking upon receive
of one of those virtual
envelopes,
what was in two field?
If the two field does
not match something
that we're happy with,
redirect the user.
How? You respond with
what status code?
301. So it is actually trivial
to fix this kind of thing.
That could still lead-- They
can't stop davidnews.com
from leading to cnn.com but
they can stop the browser
from staying there or at least
by encouraging it with that 301
to redirect elsewhere.
And this redirection is super
common, not just for harvard.edu
but even the course's
own website.
If I go to http://cs75.net
and hit enter,
notice what the URL changes to.
A few things happened there.
So this is the course's website.
What are some the things
that got inserted
automatically it seems?
Yeah.
>> [Inaudible] secure version.
>> Indeed.
So, I didn't just go
to the www version.
I also went to the
secure version, why?
We've just gotten into the habit
and I personally have gotten
to the habit of using this it
as a result for everything.
It's relatively cheap to do.
It's relatively trivial to turn
on and it's only getting cheaper
as CPUs are getting faster.
And some of you might
be familiar with--
about a year and a half ago
a tool called Firesheep was
released which was a wonderfully
free proof of concept
of something called a
session hijacking attack.
Something we'll talk
about in a few weeks time
in the context of security.
Long story short, if you
are visiting a website
that uses http://, it is
fairly trivial for someone
in your nearby wireless
vicinity whether in this room,
at Starbucks, even in your home,
if you have adversarial siblings
or roommates to login
to your Facebook account
or your Google account
or-- actually not Google,
Facebook account
or Twitter account
or any websites that's
not using https.
And that is because if
you're not using https,
nothing is encrypted and
you probably knew that.
But among the things that
aren't encrypted are things
called cookies.
So if you are just broadcasting
cookies and cookies it turns
out as we'll see in a week
or two are the mechanism via
which users are remembered as
being logged in to websites.
If you're just sending that
cookie to a website again
and again to remind you, I'm
logged in, I'm logged in,
I'm logged in, that's
not encrypted.
Anyone in Starbucks
can sniff that cookie
and with the right technical
savvy, as you will soon have,
send it as their own
and now they're logged
in to whatever you were.
It doesn't mean they
know your password
but it does mean they can
hijack your current session
so to speak.
So I retracted Google because
Google about a year or two ago,
thanks to some of the
issues in china they had
with the hacking and whatnot.
They transitioned all
their services to https.
At least if you opt
into it Facebook,
also finally offers this.
But again, we'll
come back to this.
So, a few more weeks of
insecurity in your lives
if you don't mind but we'll
come back to this and talk
about how you can have
certain defenses up.
And then tragically, even
websites that redirect
from the unencrypted version
to the encrypted version might
still be vulnerable because many
of those websites will
first do a redirect
that sends your cookie in the
clear and then it realizes, "Oh.
This should be secure."
But by then it's too late.
So, even though banking
websites almost always use this.
There have been certain
banks to be known to be not
so technically savvy who
are still leaking cookies
for reasons that
we'll soon reveal.
So I inserted the www the https
and then the stupid main page,
which is a media wiki thing
which is the tool we used
for the course's website.
It's free wiki software
and that's not really
intellectually interesting,
just their own software thing.
All right.
Any questions on http?
Well delete davidnews.com.
And again, that wouldn't
work with all web sites.
And in fact, Harvard's
probably would not work for us.
All right.
So we've teased apart
these http headers.
They'll become an invaluable
resource when it comes time
to chase down bugs or
features in your own code.
Let me take another
quick look at something
within Chrome's developer
toolbar then we'll do one last
thing with regard
to Google and see
if we can implement
a little more
of our own version of Google.
So, let me go to the elements
tab and just as a proof
of concept here, Google's
website is a little complex
underneath the hood, but let
me go ahead and right click
on Harvard University and I'm
going to choose Inspect Element.
And Inspect Element is
nice because it's going
to jump me right to the part
of the html that relates
to that portion of the page
which is wonderfully useful
for diving in deeper
to a specific place.
So that is the A href that got
me that Harvard University link.
Now suppose, I'm
actually Google's designer
and we're not quite happy
with the shade of blue
or the font size or font
face and so I want to tinker
with the web site but frankly
I don't want to have to log
in to the server and change font
size then save the file then
reload the browser and go
through all these hoops.
I kind of like to do it
inline in the browser albeit
without saving any changes.
So notice here on the right, if
you've not used Chrome before,
that-- or the developer toolbar.
Notice on the right, you have
a summary of all the styles
that relate to that specific
element in the web page.
So from top to bottom,
here's the C in CSS,
cascading top to bottom.
Here are all of the rules
that apply to that element.
So, here there's apparently
somewhere in Google CSS
and apparently the file called
search on line six, an a link,
a .w class mentioned
and all of this
where they're specifying the
color of the link and the cursor
that should be used over it.
So let me just try it for kicks.
Let me go in here and
let me change this
to let's say completely
random like orange.
So notice what I've
done up there.
I've changed the
Google's link to orange
of course not permanently and
only for the links in the page
for which that CSS rule applies.
But the point here is that this
is just a wonderfully quick
and dirty way of experimenting
especially if you're quite eager
and you want to get like
the pixel alignment perfect
in something.
Being able to just tweak it ever
so slightly here and then figure
out what the values
are and then write them
in the actual file
on the server.
It's just wonderfully useful.
Also too, if you
are trying to figure
out what font a web site uses.
I can go to computed style
because this can be a little
overwhelming like, "My God.
There's so many rules
that apply to this element
because of the cascading
nature of CSS."
Let me just look at the computed
styles which is the summary
of the end result of all of the
styles that have been applied
and if look for font family,
it indeed this is apply--
this is Arial followed
by Sans Serif.
So I know what font
now Google is using.
So just a debugging trick
it you've not used it,
this and the Network
tab we'll end
up using quite a
bit most likely.
So now back to our
own version of Google.
Unfortunately, if I type in
Harvard and hit Google search,
it doesn't go anywhere
sort of-- it kind of did.
Where did it end up?
The URL is almost the same.
It's a crazy looking URL
because its obviously a file
on my hard drive
not in the internet.
But what did change in the URL?
Yeah?
[ Inaudible Remark ]
Good. So the question
mark got appended
but no parameters got
sent so let me go ahead
and take a look at
my file again.
Oh well, no parameters were sent
because I didn't give
any of them names.
So let me go back and fix this.
Let me shrink the font so
we can see more at once
and let me do input name equals
q here and let me go back
over here and reload the page.
And now let me go
ahead and type Harvard
and now click Google search.
So now we have some progress.
So this is interesting.
Now unfortunately, Google.html
is not a web site nor is
it dynamic.
It's literally just
a static file
so you can send any parameters
you want it's just going
to ignore you every time.
But what if I kind
of cheat here?
I'm kind of in a hurry to
implement my own search engine.
I-- You know, I already
knocked off my own news site,
now I want to do my
own search engine.
Well I can actually do this,
form action should
actually go to,
let's say www.google.com/search
and I'm going
to say method equals get
in all lower case here,
slight inconsistency with
what we've seen before.
And now, let me go back
to this page, oops,
reload and now let
me type Harvard
and watch the URL
as I hit enter.
Ah, now I have implemented my
own version of Google but how?
Right. All I did was I
constructed a form I specified a
method of gets an
action that happens
to be a point B elsewhere
but because of HTTP
and because the browser
knows how to handle forms,
it compiled all of the key value
pairs, in this case just one,
q equals something put
it in the URL and sent it
to that action attribute.
Sent it to that particular URL.
So now we have implemented
our own version of Google.
Now of course it would be nice
if it were our search results
and we weren't completely
cutting corners here but that's
where we'll need something like
PHP to do things server side.
Let me pause for just a moment.
Peter, do you want to
say hello to the class?
Peter is one of our four
teaching fellows the others are
at work right now.
Do you want to say actual hello?
>> Yeah.
>> I have to come near you
with the microphone though.
Yeah. Why don't you
come this way
so the camera's a little
more readily available?
>> Hello all.
I look forward to
working with all of you
and I will see you on Wednesday.
>> OK. Excellent.
Thanks very much.
Any questions then about
Google, fake news, HTTP?
Yeah?
[ Inaudible Remark ]
Good question.
Let's see.
Had it not been named
q, would this be broken?
So let me go back into here
and let's just call it query
thinking that's a reasonable
name to give a parameter to.
Let me reload my HTML, let
me type in Harvard, enter.
And interesting,
they support query.
So let me misspell it.
OK. That's probably not
supported but maybe let's see.
OK. Let me reload,
type Harvard, enter.
OK. That just didn't work.
So they support query or q
for whatever backwards
compatibility reasons.
Good question.
Other questions?
Yeah.
[ Inaudible Remark ]
Yes. On the entirety
of Harvard's campus your
sessions can be hijacked.
So, if you have malicious
room mates or you are--
there's more technical
people around you,
you are vulnerable to this.
Session hijacking can
happen can happen anywhere
where encryption is not used.
Whether between you
and the access point,
the wireless access
point or between you
and the end point web server and
I should say especially those
of you who are from out of town,
realize that Harvard does
have fine print and rules
about not doing this to
other people otherwise they--
you can solve this problem
by expelling people,.
That's one way if you can't
do it technologically.
So, this is one of these
things where we're trying
to educate you as to how it can
be done but don't go trying this
in the dorms on campus.
Wait until you go home
on your own home network.
Other questions?
All right.
So where does this leaves us?
So we started by talking about
Google and we keep talking
about Google but just
because it's so popular
but the story applies to
really, any web site out there.
So, we talked about DNS and
the process of not only looking
up a web page's URL
or rather IP address
but also getting
your own IP address
and getting your own web server
and your own domain name.
We talked a little
bit about HTML forms
which you might be familiar
already but some of the tools
with which you can get a
little more comfortable
with diagnosing things
and debugging things
and we've written some
HTML that submits a form.
All that we haven't done
yet is actually implement
a dynamic web site.
For that we've completely
out sourced through CNN
and Google today but one
of the first things we will do
this coming Wednesday is dive
in deeper to PHP and
things like get and post
and sessions and shopping carts.
Some of the security
implications around them,
we'll dive into the
CS50 appliance
and this virtual
machine environments
with which you'll
get to play in terms
of Apache and PHP and MySQL.
So tonight, we'll
adjourn a bit early.
I'll stick around with Peter
for any one-on-one questions
you might have but otherwise,
we will see you again
on Wednesday
and after Wednesday's lecture,
we'll flow right into section
and office hours of
you have questions
about content even though the
first project won't be released
for a week or so.
All right.
See you in a couple of days.
[ Silence ]