[ Silence ]
>> Welcome back to
Computer Science S-75.
This is Lecture Nine,
our very last [laughter].
It's been a pleasure
having everyone
in the course this semester.
So, tonight we talk
about "Scalability."
So, we try to revisit some of
the topics that we've looked
at earlier in the
semester and think
about how we can deploy
applications not just
on say virtual machine, on
your laptop, or desktop,
as we've been doing
with the appliance.
But how you can scale two
servers on the Internet
and indeed multiple
so that you can handle
hundreds, or thousands,
or tens of thousands, or even
more than that in theory.
So, some of the issues
that we'll inevitably encounter
is how to go about doing this.
So, when it comes time to put
something on the Internet,
recall from Lecture Zero, that
we talked about web hosts.
So, this is by no means a list
of recommendations per se,
it's just some representative
ones
that we happen to recommend.
If only because the
teaching fellows
and I have had prior experiences
with these particular vendors.
But you can Google around and
you can see that there's many,
many, many different
options these days.
However, among the
takeaways hopefully
from the summer thus
far has been what kinds
of features should
you be looking for
or expecting minimally in
any web hosting company
that you might choose.
And in fact, not all of
these even have those
features necessarily.
[ Inaudible Speaker ]
Interesting, okay good.
So, if your country or your
work or really any network
that you happen to be on or
people that you know happen
to be on and block access
to certain IP ranges,
among them for instance,
GoDaddy in this case.
YouTube is a popular
thing to block,
Facebook is a popular
thing to block.
That can be a sticking point,
so doing a bit of due diligence
or testing first
could be a good thing.
What else should you look
for in a hosting company?
Isaac?
>> SFTP?
>> Good, SFTP in
contrast with what?
>> FTP.
>> FTP and why?
>> Because FT -- SFTP is secure.
>> Okay, good.
So, the "S" literally stands for
"Secure" and what that means is
that all of your
traffic is encrypted.
And this maybe isn't a
big deal for the files
that you're transferring,
because after all,
if you're uploading like gifs,
and jpegs, and video files
that are meant to be downloaded
by people on the web, well,
then who really cares
of you encrypt those
between your machine
and the server.
But it is important to
have what data encrypted?
Jack?
>> Usernames and
passwords [inaudible].
>> Exactly [laughter],
usernames and passwords, right?
I mean that's one of the biggest
failings of something like FTP
which granted is a fairly
dated or older protocol,
is that it sends also your user
name and password in the clear.
Which means anyone sniffing
wirelessly around you,
anyone sniffing the wire network
between point A and B can see
in the clear what your
user name and password are.
Yeah.
>> [Inaudible] posting companies
that offer unlimited everything
for a really low price.
>> Okay, good.
>> That would be due
to a virtual hosting -
>> Good.
>> -- that you wanted to
implement a system that can grow
by itself, maybe you don't want
to share the same computers,
the same server with
many others.
>> Good, so Dreamhost in
particular, I think we pulled
up their feature list and it
was ridiculous how many features
they give you, unlimited
tri-bandwidth,
unlimited storage space,
unlimited BRAM or something
like that and that just
can't possibly be real
if you're only paying
like $9.95 a month.
So there's some catch and
in general, the catch is
that they're making that
offer to you and to a 100,
to hundreds of other
customers all of whom might be
on that same machine, so you're
contending now for resources.
And the reality is they're
probably banking on the fact
that 90 something percent of
their customers don't need
that many resources but for
the one person or two persons
that do, probably going the way
of a shared host
is not necessarily
in your best interest,
certainly not something to try
to build a bigger business on.
And so, there's alternatives
to thing
like web posting
companies, there's VPSs,
a virtual private server
that you can essentially rent
for yourself and what's
the fundamental distinction
between a VPS and
a shared web post?
Axle?
>> The VPS is like
borrowed [inaudible] Linux.
It's a virtual O
machine running on cost
but it's completely
its own system.
>> Okay, good.
Well and so to be clear,
the operating system is largely
irrelevant in stream host
and shared web posts could
also be running Fedora
or any operating system
but what's key is you get your
own copy of Fedora or Ubuntu
or whatever operating system
they happen to be running.
Because in the world of VPSs,
what they do is they take
generally a super-fast server
with lots of RAM, lots of
CPU, lots of disc space,
and they chop it up
into the illusion
of multiple servers using
something called the hypervisor
or something like a product
from VMware, or Citrix,
or other companies, and even
open source providers have
platforms that allow you
to do this, run multiple -
a virtual machine on a physical
machine and so, in this world,
you're still sharing resources
but different --
in a different way.
You're instead, getting some
slice of hardware to yourself
and no one else has
user accounts
on that particular
virtual machine.
Now, with that said, the
system administrator,
the owners of the VPS company,
they themselves depending
on what hypervisor
they're using,
they might actually have
access to your virtual machine
and to your files and frankly,
if you have physical access
to the machine, you undoubtedly
have access to your files
because they can always
reboot the virtual machine,
for instance, in what's
called "single-user mode"
or "diagnostic mode" and
at that point, it's not --
they're not even prompted
for a root password.
So, realize that even
when you're using a VPS,
your data might be more
secure, more private,
from other customers
but definitely not the web
posting company itself.
If you want even more privacy
than that, you're probably going
to have to operate your
own servers that only you
or your colleagues have
physical access to.
So, here's just a list of some
of the popular VPS companies.
There is one catch - in order
to get these additional features
or these properties in a
VPS, you generally pay more.
So, instead of $10 a
month, $20 a month,
you're probably starting at $50
a month or something like that,
maybe even in the hundreds
depending on how many --
how much you want in
the way of resources.
And toward the end of today,
we'll talk about one
particular vendor of VPSs,
namely "Amazon Web
Services, Amazon EC2,"
their elastic compute cloud
that essentially lets you
self-service and spawn
as many virtual machines as you
want so long as you're willing
to pay some number of
cents per minute to have
that virtual machine
up and running.
It's actually a wonderful way
to plan for unexpected growth
because you can even
automate the process
of spawning more web servers,
more database servers,
if you happen to suddenly
get popular, even over night
or because you've been slash
dotted or posted on reedit
or the like, and then you
can have those machines
automatically power off when
interest in your product
or website has started
to subside.
All right, so how -- suppose
you are the fortunate sufferer
of a good problem which
is that your website all
of a sudden is super popular
and this website has maybe some
static web content, HTML files,
gifs, and the like, dynamic
content like PHP code,
maybe even some database stuff,
maybe some database
stuff like MySQL.
Well, how do you go
about scaling your site
so that it can handle
more users?
Well, the most straightforward
approach is generally what's
called "Vertical Scaling",
vertical in the sense that --
well, if you're running
low on RAM or you're kind
of exhausting your available
CPU cycles or you're running low
on disc space, what's
the easiest,
most obvious solution
to that problem?
Axle?
>> Get a better processor
and more RAM.
>> Good, get more RAM, more
processor, more disc space
and just throw resources
or equivalently money
at the problem.
Unfortunately, there
is a catch here.
There's sort of a ceiling
on what you can do why?
Why is vertical scaling not
necessarily a full solution?
>> Well, you can only
operate one machine so much
after a while you
can't [inaudible].
>> Yeah, exactly.
There's some real
world constraints here
where you can only buy a machine
that's maybe three gigahertz
these days, and maybe only
has a few - a handful of -
maybe a couple dozen CPUs
or cores but at some point,
you're either going to exhaust
your own financial resources
or just the state of
the art in technology
because just the world hasn't
made a machine that has
as many resources as you need.
So, you need to get a
little smarter, but at least
within here, you
have some discretion.
So, in terms of CPUs these
days, most servers have
at least two CPUs, sometimes
three or four or more
and in turn, each of those CPUs
typically has multiple cores.
In fact, most of the laptops you
guys have here these days are
generally at least duo core,
sometimes even quad core
which means that you effectively
have the equivalent of four CPUs
or four brains inside of your
computer even though they're all
inside of the same
chip essentially.
What does that mean concretely?
It means if you have a quad
core machine, you can --
your computer can literally
do four things at once.
Whereas, in yesteryear,
when you had single cores,
single CPU machines, they could
only do one thing at a time
and even though we
humans seem to think
that you're simultaneously
printing something,
you're pulling up a Google
map, you're getting email
and all this stuff seems to
be happening simultaneously,
the reality is the operating
system is scheduling each
of those programs to
get just a split second
of CPU time before
giving another program,
then another program a
split second of CPU time,
and we humans are just so slow
relative to today's processors,
that we don't even notice
that things are actually
happening serially
as opposed to in parallel.
But when you actually have quad
cores, especially in a server,
that means whereas in yesteryear
with a single core machine,
you could handle one
web request at a time.
Now, for instance, you can
handle at least four at a time,
truly in parallel and even then,
a server will typically spawn
what are called multiple
processes or multiple threads.
So, in reality, you can at
least give the impression
that you're handling many more
than even four requests
per second.
So in short, machines these
days have gotten more and more
and more CPUs as well
as more cores and
yet the funny thing here is that
we humans also aren't very good
at figuring out what to do with
all of this available hardware.
Right? Most of you, even if
you have a dual core machine,
you don't really need a dual
core machine to check your mail
or to like write an
essay for school.
You were able to do
that five, 10 years ago
with far fewer computational
resources.
Now, in fairness, there's
bloat in software and MAC OS
and Windows and Office are
just getting bigger and bigger,
so we're using those resources.
But one of the really
nice results
of this trend toward more
and more computational
resources is that,
the world has been able all the
more easily to start chopping
up bigger servers
into smaller VPSs.
And indeed, that's how Amazon
and other cloud [inaudible]
so to speak are able
to provide people
with the self-service capability
as we'll discuss a bit later.
So, within these things there
are a few things you have
discretion over.
If you've ever built a
computer, you might be familiar
with parallel ATA, or IDE,
or SATA, or SAS anyone?
Axle, what do these refer to?
>> SATA has to do
with hard drives.
>> Okay, good.
So, SATA has to do
with hard drives --
in fact, all three of those
have to do with hard drives.
Years ago, parallel ATA
or IDE hard drives were
very much in vogue.
You might still have them in
older computers these days,
desktop computers pretty much,
but you wouldn't buy a new
parallel ATA drive these days.
Instead you'd most
likely get a SATA drive
where they're 3.5 inch for a
desktop or two and a half inch
for a laptop and if you have
servers or you have lots
of money and a fancy
desktop computer,
you can go with the SAS drive.
SAS is Serial Attached SCSI
and this really just
boils down to faster.
For instance, whereas
parallel ATA
and SATA drives typically
ran at 7200 rpms per minute,
revolutions per minute,
SAS drives,
anyone know what they
typically spin at?
And for those unfamiliar, inside
of a mechanical hard drive,
there is a one or more metal
platters that literally spins,
much like an old-school
record player
where the bits are now stored.
What speed does a
SAS drive spin?
It's more than 7200 rpm.
Axle?
>> Is it 15,000?
>> Yeah, so 15,000 is where
they would typically perform,
sometimes 10,000 but 15,000.
So, just twice as fast so
that alone gives you a bit
of a speed bump.
Of course, it comes at a
price literally more money
but that's one way of
speeding things up.
So, oftentimes what people
will do is for a given website
that they're creating, if it
has a database, databases tend
to write to disc quite a bit.
Right? Every Facebook update
requires writing to disc
and then reading back
out some number of times.
So, really where you might
be touching disc a whole lot,
people can throw things like
SAS drives in their database
so that their data can be read
or written even more quickly
and what's even faster than
mechanical drives these days?
Axle?
>> Solid state drives?
>> Yeah, solid state drives,
SSDs, which have no moving parts
and as a result,
electrically perform much better
than mechanical drives.
But those too, cost more money
and they tend to be smaller
in size so whereas you can buy
like a four terabyte
SATA drive these days,
three and a half inch
for your desktop,
you can buy maximally a
768 gigabyte SSD these days
for a lot more money typically.
All right.
So, let's skip -- let's
skip RAID for now.
So, horizontal scaling --
so this is in contrast with
what we just discussed,
throwing money and throwing
more of everything at a problem.
Horizontal scaling is
sort of accepting the fact
that there's going to
be a ceiling eventually,
so why don't we instead
architect our system
in such a way that we're
not going to hit that.
Rather, we can kind of stay
below it by even using not state
of the art hardware and the
most expensive stuff we can buy,
but cheaper hardware.
Servers that might
be a few years old
or at least are not
the top of the line,
so that they'll be
less expensive.
So, rather than get few or
one really good machine,
why don't we get
a bunch of slower
or at least cheaper
machines instead,
plural number of machines?
So, this is just a picture of a
data center which is just meant
to conjure up the idea
of scaling horizontally
and actually using
multiple servers to build
out your topology but what
does this actually mean?
Well, if you have a whole
bunch of servers now,
instead of just one, how -
what's the relationship now
with Lecture Zero where we
talked about HTTP and DNS?
All right.
The world was very simple a few
weeks ago when you had a server
and it had an IP address
and that IP address
might have a domain name
or host name associated with
it and we told that story
of what happens when you type
in something dot com enter
on your laptop and you get back
the pages on that single server.
But now, we have a problem
if we have a whole aisle's
worth of web servers.
Axle?
>> Well, you're going to have to
have a way to treat each request
so it doesn't end
up at one machine.
>> Okay.
>> So, the request can be
distributed over all machines.
>> Okay, good.
So now, if we get an inbound
HTTP request, we somehow want
to distribute that request over
all of the various webservers
that we might have whether
it's two webservers or 200.
The problem really is still the
same, if it's more than one;
we have to somehow
figure that out.
So, let me put up a fairly
generic picture here -
let me flip past those
to this guy here.
So, if we have a whole bunch
of servers on the bottom here,
server one, two, dot dot dot --
and on the top, we have
some number of clients,
just random people
on the Internet.
We need to interpose now,
some kind of black box
that's generally called a
"load balancer" depicted
here as a rectangle
so that the traffic
coming from people
on the Internet is somehow
distributed or balanced
across our various
"back-end" servers so to speak.
So, it might still be the
case that server one and two
and so forth, have unique
IP addresses but now,
when a user types in something
dot com and hits enter,
what IP address should
we return?
How do we go about achieving
the equivalent of this man
in the middle who can
somehow balance load
across all end servers?
>> Well, let - return the IP
address from the balancer?
Send the request to
the load balancer
and let the load balancer handle
which computer to send it to.
>> Okay, good.
So, instead of DNS, returning
the IP address of server one
or server two or
server dot dot dot,
you could instead return the
equivalent of the IP address
of this black box,
the load balancer,
and then let the load
balancer figure out how
to actually route data to
those back-end servers.
So, that's actually
pretty clean.
So now, if the load balancer
has a public IP address,
the back-end server's
now technically --
you don't even need
public IP addresses.
They can instead have
private addresses
and what was the key
distinction between public
and private IPs back
in Lecture Zero?
Anyone -- anyone over here?
Yeah? Louis?
>> The rest of the world
can't see private IPs.
>> Exactly, so the rest
of the world by definition
of private can't see
private IP addresses.
Then -- so that seems to have
some nice privacy properties
and that if no one else can see
them, they can't address them.
So those servers, just by nature
of this privacy can't be
contacted at least directly
by random adversaries,
bad guys, on the Internet.
So, that's a plus.
Moreover, the world
has been running
out of version four
IP addresses,
the 32-bit IP address is become
into scarcity for some time now
so it's just hard or
sometimes expensive
to get enough IP addresses
to handle the various
servers that you might buy.
So this alleviates
that pressure.
Now, when we need one IP and
not multiple for our servers
because we can give
these back-end servers
like an odd number like
192.168 which most of you have
in your home routers
probably or 10 dot something
or 172.16 something, all
of those to mark the start
of a private IP address.
So, that works.
All right, so the load balancer
has its own IP address now.
It gets a request from some
client on the Internet.
How, using jargon from
Lecture Zero onward,
can the load balancer decide
or get that data to one
of the back-end servers?
How could we go about
implementing that?
Axle?
>> Well, probably first I'd
want to figure out which server
to send it to, so
you'd want to check
if somebody has available CPU
cycles that they're not using.
>> Okay.
>> So -- and once you see
that there's one server
with enough CPU cycles
to handle that request,
[inaudible] inside
your server network --
>> Okay.
>> -- to that machine to
get back whatever it is
that the client requested
and then the load balancer
sends it [inaudible].
>> Excellent.
So, this request arrives
then at the load balancer,
the load balancer
decides to whom he wants
to send this packet, server
one or two or dot dot dot,
and you can make that decision
based on any number of factors.
So, Axle proposed doing it based
on load like who is the busiest
versus the least busy.
Odds are I should send my
request to the least busy server
in the interest of optimizing
performance all around.
So, let's assume that
there's some way as demarcated
by those black arrows,
like talking
to those back-end servers and
saying, "Hey, how busy are you?
Let me know."
So, now the load balancer
figures out it wants
to send this particular
request to server one,
so it sends that request
to server one using
similar mechanisms,
TCP IP much like the
packet, how it traveled
to the load balancer
in the first place.
The server then gets the packet,
does its thing and says, "Oh,
they want some HTML
file, here it is."
The response goes to
the load balancer,
the load balancer then responds
to the client, and voila.
So, that works.
What are some alternatives
to load balancing based
on the actual load
on the server?
So, load in general refers
to how busy a server is.
So, what's an even
simpler approach than that,
because that -- frankly,
that sounds a little complex?
We've not talked at all about
how one device can query another
for characteristics
like, "How busy are you?"
Even though it's possible.
Axle?
>> Well, first let me point
out a downside with that,
you [inaudible] every file --
every file the website
has on every server.
So, if you would instead say
have one server containing all
the HTML and one running
and containing all the PHP,
you would then see --
well, okay, bad example.
One example of one server
with all the images
[inaudible] HTML --
>> Okay.
>> -- [inaudible]
to request an image.
It sends it to the
image server --
>> Okay.
>> -- and if it's an HTML
request, to the HTML server.
>> Okay, good.
So, the implication of the
previous story that Axle told is
that under this model, server
one, two, and so forth,
all need to be identical, have
the same content which is nice
and then it doesn't matter
to whom you send the request.
The downside is now, you're
using N times as much disc space
as you might otherwise need to,
but that's perhaps the price you
pay for having this redundancy
or to having this
horizontal scalability.
Or instead, you could
have dedicated servers --
these are for HTML,
these are for gifs,
these are for movie files and
the like, and you could do
that just by having different
URLs, different host names.
This is, for instance,
"Images dot something dot com."
"This is videos dot
something dot com."
And then the load
balancer could take
into account the host
HTTP header to decide
which direction it should go in.
So, that could work for us.
All right, so what's an
even simpler puristic
than asking a back-end server,
"How busy are you right now?"
Like, if you have no
idea how to do that?
How instead, could
we balance load
across an arbitrary
number of servers?
Think again back
to Lecture Zero.
You can do all of this with only
Lecture Zero under our belt.
So, let's quickly
tell the story.
I type in something
dot com into a browser;
I hit "Enter," what happens?
Jack?
>> We create a packet to send.
>> Okay, packet to send
-- to whom do we send it?
>> We send it to someplace that
will determine the IP address
of where we're sending it to.
>> Okay, good -- something that
will determine the IP address
of where we're sending it to
-- what's that thing called?
Isaac, what's that called?
>> A router?
>> Not router -- the
routers get involved but --
>> The DNS.
>> The DNS server, domain name
system server, so that server
in the world, whole bunches
of them that whose purpose
in life is to translate host
names to IPs and vice versa.
So, I'm going to
pause the story there.
That seems to be an opportunity
now for us to return something.
Yeah?
>> Could you do some DNS tricks
and return a different
IP address based
on what the user requested?
>> Good, so this black
box, this load balancer,
maybe it's just a
fancy DNS setup.
Whereby instead of
returning the IP address
of the load balancer itself,
maybe instead the DNS server
just returns the IP address
of server one the
first time someone asks
for something dot com.
And the next time someone
requests something dot com,
it returns the IP address
of server two followed
by server three followed by
dot dot dot and the wrapping
around eventually
to server one again.
So, this is actually
generally called "Round Robin"
and you can do this
fairly easily.
This is just a snippet of a
popular DNS server called BIND,
Berkeley Internet Name
Demon, I believe is the D.
And this just suggests
that if you want
to have multiple IP
addresses for host name called
"dub dub dub" you mention
"A" which denotes A record
and just refers to
an end pointer here.
But A is the same
as in Lecture Zero
and then you just enumerate the
IP address one after the other
and by default, this particular
DNS server, very popular one,
BIND, will return a different
IP address for each request.
So, that's nice.
It's simple.
Again, it uses only
some knowledge
from Lecture Zero even though
granted, you have to know how
to configure the DNS server,
but you don't need any fancy
bi-directional communication
with the back-end
servers in this model.
So, that's nice.
But there's a price we
pay for the simplicity.
If we only do Round Robin,
where again, we just spit
out a different IP
address each time
and let me make this
more concrete just
so this isn't quite as abstract.
Let me open up a terminal
program here and do NS Lookup
for name server lookup
of Google.com.
This is exactly what Google
does, at least in part.
Their load balancing
solution is more sophisticated
than this list suggests,
but indeed Google's DNS server
returns multiple IP addresses
each time.
So, if this is so simple to
implement, what's the catch?
Axle?
>> It's not a very smart
solution because just --
there could be -- the case could
be that one server gets all
of the really tough
and hard requests --
>> Good.
>> -- that take a lot
of processing power.
The other ones just
get the [inaudible].
There's no way to know that.
>> Good, so just by bad luck,
one of the servers could
just get a really --
a real power user, someone
who is really doing something
computationally difficult.
Like, I don't know,
what's a good --
sending lots of mail or someone
else is just kind of logging in
and poking around at a much
slower rate and we could come
up with even more sophisticated
examples than that.
But over time, server
one might just happen
to get more heavy weight
users than other servers.
So, what's the implication?
Well, Round Robin is still
going to keep sending more
and more users to that server
one-Nth of the time just
by nature of Round Robin.
So, that's not so good.
What else causes problems here
or what else breaks potentially?
So, back to the Lecture Zero
story, I type something dot com,
I hit "Enter", my browser
sends a request to the DNS --
or my operating systems sends
a request to the DNS server,
it gets the IP address
and in this model, it's --
the IP address of one of these
servers, then I send my packet
as Jack proposed to
that particular server,
get back a response, story ends.
But then a few seconds
later, I visit another link
on something dot
com and hit "Enter",
which part of the
story now changes?
Jack?
>> Is it now going to send to
the same server [inaudible]
or does it send it
to a new server?
>> Good question.
>> Exactly where
it's coming from?
>> So, how does the story change
and that'll give us the answer?
Axle?
>> Well, it has to send it
to a new server otherwise
Round Robin wouldn't work.
>> Oh, ideally, yes.
If you want a truly
uniform distribution
across all end servers,
then the DNS server has
to return another
response and I'd argue,
the DNS server will return a
different response the next time
it is queried.
But --
>> Oh, it's not queried.
>> Why?
>> Because it's saved.
>> Saved or --
>> No, but it's -- the --
the IP address is stored --
>> Where?
>> -- [inaudible] open session
otherwise it's really useless
to query the DNS server for the
same thing over and over again.
>> Good. So, recall these
caches back in Lecture Zero.
We talked about the
implications of the good parts
of caching whereby as Axle's
proposing, there's no reason
for Chrome or IE to send the
same DNS request every single
time you click a link
on something dot com.
That would just be
a waste of time.
You're going to lose some number
of milliseconds every time
that happens or worse
yet, a second or two.
So, instead your operating
system typically caches
these responses.
Your browser typically caches
these responses as well,
and so you just don't
need to do those lookups.
So, if you do happen to be that
power user that's doing a heck
of a lot of work of
whatever sort on server one,
the next guy is going to
be sent to server two,
not you with your
subsequent request.
So, caching too can contribute
to a disproportionate amount
of load on certain servers
largely due to bad luck.
Indeed in DNS, we
didn't spend much time
on this particular detail
but there's typically
expiration times, TTLs,
Time to Live values associated
with an answer from a DNS server
and that's typically an hour,
or five minutes, or a day.
It totally depends
on who controls the DNS
server, what the value is.
But that suggests too, that
if you are this power user
on server one, it might be a few
minutes, or hours, or even days,
until you get assigned to
some other server simply
because your TTL
has expired by then.
So, it's nice and simple.
We can do it with a
simple configuration change
but it doesn't necessarily
solve all of our problems.
So, in fact, the approach Axle
proposed first is actually
pretty good whereby you don't
use DNS space to Round Robin.
Rather, more sophisticated
approach would be
to let the load balancer to
decide to whom to send you
in the back-end and the
load balancer can make
that decision using any
number of puristics.
It could even use Round Robin
or randomness because at
that point, you don't have
to worry about caching issues
because the DNS server
has only returned one IP.
So -- but that still
leads you to the risk
that you'll be sent -- putting
too much load on some server
so we could take, for instance,
server load into
account at that point.
But there is something
else that breaks.
If we fast forward mid-semester
to when we started talking
about cookies and HTTP
and sessions and PHP.
To spark discussion, I propose
that sessions have
just broken in PHP.
If our back-end servers
are PHP-based websites
and they are using the
session super global,
load balancing seems
to break this model.
Why, Jack?
>> Because now, the different
servers have different people
sessions so although one might
have my session and by then,
I'm redirecting from
server one to server two,
server two might
not have my session.
>> Exactly.
>> Therefore, everything's lost.
>> So, sessions recall, tend
to be specific to
the given machine.
We saw examples involving
slash temp
which is a temporary
directory on the Linux system
where sessions were
typically saved as text files,
serialized text files.
So, that means though, that
your session might be sitting
on the hard drive of
server one and yet if
by random chance you are sent
by a Round Robin to server two
or server three instead of
server one, in the worst case,
you're going to see the same
website but you're going
to be told to log in
again for instance,
because that server doesn't
know that you've logged in.
Okay, find -- you kind of
bite your tongue and you type
in your user name and
password again and hit "Enter"
and suppose you're
a really good sport
and you do this for
all end servers.
You have no idea why something
dot com keeps prompting you
to log in but eventually, you
will have a session cookie
on all of those servers.
The catch then though is that
if something dot com is an
E-Commerce site and
you're adding things
to your shopping cart, now
you literally have put a book
in your cart over here, a
different book in this cart,
a different book in this
cart and when you check out,
you can't check out
the aggregate.
So, this is a very
non-trivial problem now.
Axle?
>> But this wouldn't
happen if you --
if you had dedicated machines
[inaudible] one machine running
PHP and then one machine
serving all the images.
>> Very true.
So, if we have horizontally
scaled in the sense
that we've factored
out disparate services,
this is our PHP server,
this is our gif server,
this is our video server.
Then indeed, this
problem would not arise
because presumably all the
PHP traffic would get routed
to the PHP server.
But an obvious push-back
to that solution is what?
Isaac?
>> Well, if one of them crashes
and you lose all images or --
>> Okay, good.
There's no redundancy
which is not good
for uptime if anything breaks.
Axle?
>> And also, well at
some point in time,
if you get popular enough,
that one PHP server's not going
to be able to handle
everything --
>> Good.
>> -- it need to [inaudible].
>> The end of story's the same.
As soon as you get popular,
you get too much load
for a single PHP
server, then we have
to solve this problem anyway.
So, how do we go about
solving this problem?
This seems to be a real pain,
this one and to be clear;
the problem now is that inasmuch
as sessions are typically
implemented per server
in the form of like a text
file like we saw in slash temp,
then you can't really
use Round Robin.
You can't really use load
-- true load balancing,
taking into account each
server's load because you need
to make sure that Alice,
if she's initially sent
to server one, subsequently
gets sent to server one again,
and again, and again, for
at least, you know, an hour
or a day or some amount of time
so that her session is useful.
Jack?
>> Is there a way to create
a server that's especially
dedicated to store
everyone's session
and all the sessions
are started there and --
>> Excellent.
Yes, so absolutely.
We could just continue this
idea of factorization and factor
out not the various
types of files,
but a service like
session state.
So, if we instead had a
file server, you know,
like a big external hard drive,
so to speak, that is connected
to all of the servers,
one and two and three,
so that anytime they
store session data,
they store it there instead
of on their own hard drive.
Then this way, we
could share state.
So indeed, that could
be a solution here.
Axle?
>> What -- I don't know if the
load balancer has that function,
but [inaudible] instead
of having an extra server,
that all the other servers
can query the load balancer
because all traffic goes
through that anyhow.
What if the load balancer
stores the session?
>> Okay, so that's
not bad at all.
So, we already have a
man in the middle here.
It's a black box but there's no
reason it couldn't be a server
with hard disc space.
So, why not put the sessions
on the load balancer?
That could absolutely work.
So, let me difficult then and
whether we put the sessions
on the load balancer
or whatever --
that's no longer a load balancer
then, it's obviously doing more.
It's more of a server
that happens
to be balancing load
and storing sessions.
Whether we put sessions there
in that black box or elsewhere
in a new box on the screen,
we seem to have introduced
a weakness now
in our network topology because
what if that machine breaks?
It would seem to be the case
that even though we have
N servers which in theory,
those guys are never all
going to die at once,
assuming that it's not
the power, electricity,
or something stupid like
that that's somehow related
to all of them.
But odds are they're
not all just going to up
and die simultaneously so we
have really good redundancy
in our server model right now.
But as soon as we introduce
just a database or file server
for our sessions, if that guy
dies, then what was the point
of spending all this money on
all these back-end servers?
Our whole site goes down because
we have no ability to remember
that people are logged in
if we can't remember they're
logged in.
No one can buy anything.
So, how do we fix that problem?
So, we've solved one problem
but if you think of that sort
of old visual where you have
like a garden hose with lots
of leaks in it and you plug
one of them with one hand,
all of a sudden a new
leak springs up elsewhere.
That's kind of what's
happened here.
We solved the problem
of shared state but now,
we've sacrificed some
robustness, some redundancy.
How do we now fix the latter?
Axle?
>> It's probably not the
solution you're looking for,
that the hardware on your little
data center could be built
such that things like the
hard drive [inaudible] missing
RAID type.
>> Okay good so we could just
use sort of different approach
to storing our data and
rather than just store it
on the hard disk as usual, we
could use something called RAID.
So actually this
is good way to tie
in the thing we skipped
a moment ago.
Let me just pull up
something to write on here.
So Redundant Array
of Independent Disks is a
technology more succinctly known
as RAID.
RAID can actually be used
in desktop computers these
days even though it's not all
that common.
Some companies like Dell and
Apple make it relatively easy
to use RAID on your system,
and what does this mean?
Well RAID can come in
a few different forms.
There's something
called RAID zero,
there's something called
RAID1, there's something RAID5,
there's something called RAID6,
there's something called RAID10
and there's even more,
but there are some
of the simplest ones
to talk about.
So all of these technog -- all
of these variance of RAID assume
that you have multiple hard
drives in your computer
for different purposes
potentially.
So in the world of RAID1 --
RAID zero you typically
have two hard drives
that are of identical size.
Terabyte, two terabytes, 512
gigabytes whatever it is,
two identical hard drives
and you do what's called
stripe data across them.
Whereby every time the
Operating System wants
to save a file especially big
files, it will first write
to this drive a bit
then to this one,
then to this one.
The motivation being these
hard drives are typically large
and mechanical with
spinning platters
like we discussed earlier,
and so it might take this
guy a little while to write
out some number of bits.
Now it's going to be
split second in reality
but that's a split second
we don't really have
when we're trying to
service lots of users.
So striping allows me to write
some data here then here,
then here then here, then here
then here effectively doubling
the speed at which I can write
files especially large ones
to disks.
So RAID zero is nice
for performance.
However, RAID1 gives you
a very different property.
With RAID1 you still have two
hard drives but you mirror data
so to speak across them,
so that anytime you write
out a file you store it
both places simultaneously.
There's a bit of performance
overhead to writing it
in two places albeit in
parallel, but the upside now is
that either of these
drives can die
and your data is still
perfectly intact,
and it's actually an
amazing technology
because if even you
just have this
in your desktop computer,
you have two drives.
One of them dies just because
of bad luck, there's a defect
or its multiple years old
and it just up and died,
so long as the other
one is still working.
The theory behind RAID is that
you can then run to the store,
buy another hard drive that's
at the same size or bigger,
plug it into your
computer, boot back up,
and most typically
automatically,
the RAID array will
rebuild itself whereby all
of the data that's
on the remaining drive will
copy itself automatically
over to the new one
and after a few minutes
or hours you're back
to a safer place.
Whereby now even the other
drive can up and die.
Sometimes you have to run a
command or choose a menu option
to induce that but
typically it's automatic.
You can do it even sometimes
in some machines while
the computer is still
on so you don't even have
to suffer any downtime,
so that's great.
RAID10 is essentially the
combination of those two.
You typically use four drives
and you have both striping
and redundancy so you sort of
get the best of both worlds,
but costs you twice as
much cause you need twice
as many hard disks.
RAID5 and RAID6 are kind of
nice middle grounds with RAID1
or nice variance of RAID1
whereby RAID1 is kind
of pricy, right?
Rather than buy two -- one
hard drive I literally have
to spend twice as much
and get two hard drives.
RAID5 is a little more versatile
whereby I typically have say
three drives, four drives,
five drives, but only one
of them is used for redundancy.
So if I get five,
one terabyte drives,
I have four terabytes
of usable space.
So I'm only sacrificing
one-fifth in that case
of my available disk
capacity whereas
in RAID1 you're sacrificing
one half so 50% of it.
So RAID5, you just
get better economy
at scale whereby
you can grow bigger
and you still have
some redundancy.
So in RAID5 if you have three
or four or five hard drives
in the array, one of them
can die, any of them.
You run to the store
put in a new one
and you haven't lost any data.
RAID6 is even better, what
does RAID6 do, do you think?
Axle?
>> Well I think two
drives can die.
>> Exactly in RAID6 any two
drives can die you still won't
have lost any data, and
so long as you've run
to the store fast
enough and put in one
or both drives again,
you'll be good to go.
Of course the price you pay
with RAID6 is literally
another hard drive
but at least now you can
maybe sleep a bit better
at night knowing that man,
two of my hard drives has
to die before I have to
really worry about this.
So these are really
nice technologies and so
as Axle proposes here, the
upside of using something
like that in whatever file
server were storing our shared
sessions is we can at least
decrease the probability
of downtime at least
related to hard disks.
Unfortunately it still has a
power cord that someone can trip
over or the power
supply could die.
It still has RAM that
could go on the fritz,
a motherboard that could die.
Any number of things
could still happen,
but at least we can
throw redundancy inside
of the confines of
a single server
and this can definitely
help with our uptime
and with our robustness.
And indeed with actual
servers that you would buy
for a data center,
not so much of a home.
It's very common for computers
to have not only multiple
hard drives and lots
of multiple banks of RAM,
and they would often have
multiple power supplies as well.
And it's actually a really
cool technology there too.
If one of your power
supplies dies,
you can literally pull it out.
The machine keeps running,
you put in a new one
and then it spreads the amperage
across two power supplies once
both are back up and running,
all very hot swappable.
Amazing technology these
days and as an aside,
if you still own a
desktop computer,
there is no reason you
shouldn't use RAID these days.
It is just very good practice
since it will allow you
to avoid downtime and data
loss with higher probability.
Okay, but someone tripped over
the power code, someone tripped
over both power codes
in the case
of redundant power supplies.
So Axle's solution and even mine
with redundant power supplies
hasn't solved the problem
of shared storage becoming all
of a sudden a single
point of failure.
So what else could we do
to still get the
property of shared state.
So it doesn't matter what
backend server I end up on
but I instead get -- I
still get to the ability
to suffer some downtime.
Well shared storage can come
in a bunch of different ways,
so we talked really about
things as a file server
but this can be incarnated
with very specific technology.
And just to rattle them off even
though we won't talk about them
in much technical detail, Fiber
Channel, FC, is a very fast,
a very expensive technology
that you can use in offices,
in data centers not
so much the home
to provide very fast shared
storage across server.
So that's just one type of
file server if you will.
ISCSI is another technology
that uses IP, Internet Protocol,
and uses Ethernet cables to
exchange data with servers
so that's a nice somewhat
cheaper way of exchange --
of having a shared file server
that can be used by multiple --
actually in the case of
ISCSI you typically use it
with it single servers.
So let me re-track that,
that is not a solution
to our current cookie problem.
But what about MySQL?
All right, we use that
for a couple of weeks,
MySQL seems to be
a nice candidate
because it's already a
separate server potentially.
Could not the backend servers
just write their session objects
to a database, they
definitely could.
So just because you're
storing things in --
just because we usually
store things like user data
and user generated
and a database,
doesn't mean we can't
store metadata
like our cookie information
as well,
or that too comes
from users though.
NFS, Network File System,
this is just a protocol
that you can use to implement
the idea that Axle proposed
of a shared file system.
It just means you've
got one server
and you're exposing
your hard disk
to multiple other computers.
But again, we haven't really
solved the problem of downtime,
so what's the most obvious
way of mitigating the risk
that your single file
server will go down?
Axle?
>> Keep your copy of the
sessions in another location.
>> Good, right?
If it's not -- if
you don't have --
if you're worried about
the one file server going
down well the obvious
solution even though money
and some technical
complexity will just get two.
Now somehow you have to
figure out how to sink the two
so that one has a copy of the
other's data and vice versa.
So let's actually come back to
that issue, it's generally known
as replication but it
is something we can
potentially achieve.
But before we segue to
distribution of things,
let's finish out this
Load Balancer question.
So how do you go about
implementing this black box?
Well these days you actually
have a bunch of options.
In software, you can do
things relatively easily
with a browser, pointing
and clicking using things
like amazons, elastic load
balancer, or a scenario
for which we'll talk
about a bit later.
HAProxy, High Availability
Proxy,
is free open source software
that you can run on a server
that can do a load
balancing as well using any --
either of the characteristics we
discussed earlier around Robin
or actually taking load
into account somehow.
Linux Virtual Server, LVS
is another free software,
a piece of software you
can use and the world
of hardware people have made big
business out of Load Balancers,
Barracuda, Cisco, Citrix,
F5 are some of the most
popular vendors here.
Most of whom are atrociously
overpriced for what they do.
So case and point like
Citrix is a popular company
that sells Load Balancers
take a guess
as to what a Load Balancer
might cost you these days?
It's a highly variable range
but there's different
models, but take a guess?
How much of that
black buck cost?
Isaac?
>> Thousands.
>> Definitely in the
thousands, indeed.
In fact, we have a small
one, so to speak --
small one relatively
speaking on campus
that was $20,000 and guess what?
That one is cheap.
So you can literally
spend on these kind
of things granted not, this is
what the per cost the weight
you've read after the
semester ends today.
But a $100,000 for
a Load Balancer
or even generally a pair of
Load Balancers so that either
of them can die and the
other one can stay alive.
So in the world of
enterprise hardware,
these ideas we're talking
about are ridiculously
priced typically
because of support
contracts and the like.
So just realize software
is number one on the list
because there are other ways
to achieve this much
more inexpensively.
Indeed for years one of the
courses I teach we used HAProxy
to balance load because
it was so relatively easy
to set up and 100$ free.
So realize the same ideas
can be both bought and set
up on your own quite
readily these days.
All right let's pause here
and when we come back we'll
take a look at some issues
of like caching, of
replication in databases
and also how we can
speed up PHP a bit.
Let's take our five
minute break here.
All right we're back
and I almost forgot,
we have one other
solution to this problem
of the need for sticky sessions.
Sticky sessions meaning
that when you visit a
website multiple times,
your session is somehow
preserved even
if there're multiple
backend servers.
So shared storage was the idea
we really vetted quite a bit
and we didn't quite get
to a perfect solution
since even though we
factored out the storage,
and put everyone's
cookies or session objects
on the same server, it feels
like we need some redundancy
but we'll come back
to that in the context
of MySQL in just a bit.
But what about cookies?
I propose that cookies
themselves could offer a
solution to the problem
of sticky sessions
and again sticky
sessions means even
if you visit a website multiple
times, you're still going to end
up with the same session
object, or more specifically,
you're still going to end up on
the same backend server, Axle?
>> Either of the -- store
which server you want
to go to in a cookie.
>> Okay.
>> Or store everything
in cookies
but that's not a good solution.
>> Store or -- okay, yes,
so storing everything
in cookies is probably bad
because one then it's really
starting to violate privacy
because rather than store a big
a key, you're going to store
like the ISPNs of all the
books in your shopping cart
and that might be fine but
feels like your roommates
and family members don't need
to know what is in your cookies.
Moreover cookies
typically have a finite size
of a few kilobytes, so
there's definitely going
to be circumstances in which you
just can't fit everything you
want to in the cookie.
So you know an interesting
idea but probably not the best,
so you could store the ID
of a server in a cookie
so that the user, the second,
and third, and fourth times,
they visit your website
as by following links
or coming back some other
time, they are going
to present the equivalent
of a hand stamp saying,
"Hey I was on backend server
1, send me there again."
So that's a pretty nice
idea, there is one,
at least one downside
here, what do you like --
what do you not like
potentially about this idea
of storing inner cookie that
gets put on user's browser,
that they subsequently transmit
back to you the number of,
or the ID of the server to
which they should be sent.
Axle?
>> Well from runner expiration.
>> Expiration in what sense?
>> All of cookie
expires after [inaudible]
>> Okay, so eventually cookie
is going to expire though,
we saw a couple lectures just
ago, we couldn't make it expire
in 10 years if we really
wanted to and frankly,
we're never going to avoid that
even if we had a single server,
cookies could eventually expire.
So at least that's not a new
problem, so I'm not too worried
about expiration now, because
that's not a problem new
to us simply because
of load balancing.
Does anything not feel
right about storing the idea
of the server in the cookie?
>> What if the IP changes?
>> Yeah, so if we just
put like the backend IP
so the private IP address
in the cookie, you know what
of the IP changes, what if
that -- what if the IP changes,
so that's a little
problematic and it's also one
of these principle things like,
you don't really need to reveal
to the world what your
IP address scheme is,
it's not necessarily
something they could exploit
but it's just the whole world
doesn't need to know that.
Moreover we can implement
the same idea
by still storing a cookie
on the user's computer
but why don't we
take the PHP approach
of let's just store
a big random number
and then have the
load balancer remember
that that big random number
belongs to server one.
And this other big
random number belongs
to server two and so forth.
So a little more work
on the load balancer
but in this way then, we're
really not putting any states
that might change or might
be a little privacy revealing
on the actual user's computer.
Moreover we also take away
the ability for them to spoof
that cookie just to get
access to some other server.
Now whether or not
they could anything
with that trick is unclear
but at least we take away
that ability altogether
so there's no surprises.
All right, so cookies indeed are
something that these black boxes
of -- so load balancers tend
to do whereby you
can configure them
to insert a cookie
themselves, it doesn't just have
to be a backend web server
that generates cookies,
the load balancer similarly
could be inserting a cookie
with the set cookie header
that the end user then
subsequently sends back
so that we can remember
what backend server
to send the user to.
Now if the user has cookies
disabled well then this whole
system breaks down but
again so does a lot
of functionality we've
discussed this far this semester
but there are sometimes
some workarounds.
So a word on PHP, PHP in
an interpreted languages is
in general tend to get a
bad rep for performance
because they tend not to
be as a high as performing
as a compiled language like
C plus plus or C or the like.
However there are some ways to
mitigate this, there is notion
of PHP Acceleration whereby
you can run a PHP program,
the source code through php.exe,
the interpreter on the system
and it turns out that PHP does
typically compile that file
in a sense, down to something
that's more efficiently
executed, much like
Java complied something
down to something
called Bi code.
But you typically --
PHP throws the results
of that compilation away.
Whereby it does it
again and again
for every subsequent request,
however with very simple --
with relatively straight --
forward and free the
available software,
you can install a
PHP Accelerator here
in just four possibilities
that essentially eliminate
that discarding of
the PHP Opcodes
and instead keep them around.
So in other words the first
time someone visits your site,
the PHP file is going to be
interpreted and some Opcodes
for performance generated
but they are not going
to be thrown away
because the next time you
or someone else visits the site,
that PHP file is not going have
to be reparsed and
reinterpreted,
the Opcodes are just going to be
executed, so you get the benefit
of some added performance.
Now the only got you is
if you ever change any
of your dot php files, you have
to throw away the cached Opcodes
but these various tools
typically do that for you.
Python has a similar mechanism
where you'll get dot py files
or your source code files
but dot pyc files are
the complied versions
that can be executed
more quickly,
so the same idea
is at play here.
So this one of these things
that is relatively easy and free
to enable, and gives you
all the more performance,
specifically the ability
to handle all the more requests
per seconds in the context
of a PHP based website.
So what about caching too?
Caching in general is a
great thing, it solves some
of our DNS concerns early
on but it introduced others
because caching can be a bad
thing if some value has changed
but you have the old one.
But Caching can be
implemented in the context
of dynamic websites in a few
different ways, so I propose
that through HTML,
through MySQL,
and through something
called memcached,
we can achieve some
caching benefits here.
So this is a screen shot of
one of the most 1990s websites
out there and this was not
even taken in the 1990s,
this was taken a couple of
years ago and I just visited
out of curiosity craigslist
today, it still looks the same.
So what's interesting
about Craigslist is
that it is a dynamic website
and that you can fill out a form
and post a for sale ad or
roommate ad or of the like,
and the website does
actually change but it's --
if we zoom in on this and it's
going to be a little blurry
because of the screen
shot, the URL that's
up there is actually dot html
even though it's barely readable
at this resolution.
Which is to suggest
that craigslist is
apparently accepting user input
through forms for
instance whoever wrote
up this job advertisement
sometime ago
but then Craigslist
it's speeding it
out as a dot html
file as opposed
to storing it where or in what?
Axle?
>> I suppose to storing the
data that [inaudible] page
in the database then
printing it in PHP.
>> Yeah so this is in stark
contrast of what we've done
for project zero, project
one, we're using PHP
as the backend whereby you store
data like this, like server side
and maybe an XML file
or more realistically
in a MySQL database or similar,
and then you generate a page
like this dynamically.
So why is Craigslist
doing this apparently?
Could just be they
are stuck in the '90s
but there's compelling
reason too, Axle?
>> Well if they store the actual
HTML file then they don't have
to regenerate it every
time they it's visited.
>> Yeah exactly, if they are
storing the html file they just
don't have to regenerate it
every time it's re visited,
so this itself is
caching, it's not caching
in any particularly fancy way,
you're just generating the html
and saving it in something
called like something.html
and storing it on disk.
And the upside of this is
that web servers like Apache,
you're really, really, really
good and fast at just spitting
out bits, just spitting raw
static content like a GIF,
a JPEG, and HTML file but the
performance optimization these
days generally relate to the
languages like PHP, and PYTHON,
and RUBY where you're trying
to fine-tune performance,
but if all you have to do is
respond to a TCPIP request
with a bunch of bytes from disk.
That's relatively straight --
forward these days and so
they're taking advantage
of the performance presumably
of serving up static content
but this comes at a cost.
What's the downside of this
file based caching approach?
Someone else?
Nothing we've this far is
sort of a complete win,
there's always a got you, Louis?
>> Space.
>> Okay so space, so we're
storing it on disk and internet,
if you either post
it on Craigslist,
they are also storing it
somewhere in a database
because they do let
go back and edit it,
it's just Craigslist
is one of the sites
where reads are probably
much more common than writes.
Indeed when people
visit craigslist,
they are probably flipping
through reading pages as opposed
to posting lots, and
lots, and lots of ads all
at the same time, so there
some redundancy there
that's unfortunate.
Axle?
>> Yeah that to -- just
to build upon that,
you will be storing lots of
code that you use on every page
over again, plus it's not
a very elegant solution
to have it fixed on your
server containing 10,000 files.
>> Okay good so there's
redundancy while actually all
these thousands of files,
there's redundancy too
just in the basic stuff.
Like you have the same HTML
tag, the same body tag,
the same link tag, the same
grip tag in every single page
if they're indeed just
static HTML files.
So whereas, you get some
benefits of using something
like PHP and recall MVC
discussion where we factored
out template code, like
the header and the footer,
so that we stored
it in one place
and not thousands of places.
Craigslist is kind of
sacrificing that feature
and going with this instead,
so in the end it's probably
a calculated trade off,
you get much better performance
presumably from just serving
up the static content, but the
price you pay is more disk space
but at the same time, you know
for a few hundred dollars you
can typically get even bigger
hard drives these days, so
maybe that's actually the lesser
of the evils.
But there is one -- there
is another big got you here,
if you've generated tens of
thousands of craigslist pages
that look like this,
what's the implication now
and maybe why are they
stuck in the '90s?
>> Well I decide to add -- well
change the background color.
>> Good
>> Some change the design
part of it which is necessary
but you can't do that
without editing each one
of those ten thousand files
and that could be automatically
but it's much harder than just
editing the generic template
that generates it.
>> Exactly, if you want
to change the aesthetics
of the page and add a
background color, change the CSS
or make it the font other
than Times New Roman,
it's nontrivial now because
assuming this is a fully intact
HTML file with no server
side include mechanism,
no like require mechanism
like you have in PHP.
You have to now change the
background color in tens
of thousands of files,
unless maybe you at least put
in a CSS file but even then
if it's a less trivial
change than color.
Suppose you want to restructure
the HTML of the page,
then you really have to do
a massive find and replace
or more realistically probably
regenerate all ten thousand plus
pages and I'm -- we latch on
to ten thousand arbitrarily
but there's a lot of
pages in this case.
So upsides and downsides,
they're one of the few people
in the internet who do
this particular approach
but it does have some value.
And I think the last time I
read up on statics they get
by with relatively little
hardware as a result
which is definitely compelling.
So MySQL query cache, this is
a mechanism that we didn't use,
but it's so easily enabled on
a typical server with MySQL,
there's a file called my.cnf
for your configuration file.
And you can simply
add a directive
like query cached type equals
1, and then re start the server
to enable the query cache which
pretty much does what it says.
The -- if you execute a command
like select foo from bars
where bars equal 1,
2, 3, that would be --
could be slow the first
time you execute it
if you don't have an index, or
if you have a really huge table.
But the next time you execute
it, if the query cache is on
and if that row hasn't
changed, the response is going
to come back much more quickly.
So MySQL provides
this kind of caching
for identically executed queries
which might certainly
happen a lot
if the user is navigating
your website going forward
and back quite a bit.
Memcached is an even
more powerful mechanism;
Facebook has made
great use of this
over the years especially
initially.
Memcached is a memory cache,
so it is a piece of software,
a server that you
run on a server,
it can be on the same
server as your web server,
it can be on a different
box altogether,
but it essentially
is a mechanism
that stores whatever
you want in RAM.
And it does this with -- in
the PHP context with codes
like this, so this
Memcached can be used
by all sorts of languages.
Here is PHP zone interface
to it and you use Memcached
as follows, you first connect
to the Memcached server
using Memcached connect
which is very similar in
spirit to MySQL connect
which you might recall
from a few lectures back.
Then we try in this
example to get a user,
so the context here is,
it's pretty expensive
to do select star from
users on my database table
because I've got millions
of users in this table
and I'd really rather
not execute
that query more often
than I have to.
I'd rather execute it once,
save the results in RAM
and the next time I need
that user, go into the RAM,
go into the cache to
get that user rather
than touching the database.
So there's this sort of
tier performance objectives,
disk is slow, right spinning
disks are specially slow,
but faster serve up so
generally you might want
to store something instead of
on disk, you want to store it
in a table that has indexes
so that you can search
it more quickly.
For instance think
back to project zero,
the XML file is relatively
slow but at the same time,
anytime you wanted to search it,
you had to load it from disk,
build a dome thanks
to the simple XML API then
search it, kind of annoying.
It would be nice if we
could skip the disk step
so that things would just be
faster and thus, was born MySQL
on project one, MySQL
is a server
which means it's always running,
it's using some RAM so in
that case you have the
ability to execute queries
on a data that's hopefully
in RAM but if it isn't you
at least have the opportunity
to define indexes, primary keys,
unique keys, index fields, so
that at least you can search
that data more readily than
you can with say XPath in XML.
So the next step is not
even to use a database
because database queries
can be expensive relative
to just a cache which is
just a key value store.
I want to give you x equals
y and the next time I ask
for x you give me y
and I want it quick,
much faster than a
database would return it.
So here we've gone and connected
to the memory cache daemon,
the sever, and the second line
I am trying to get something
from the cache, the arguments
the Memcached get take the first
argument is a reference
to the cache that you want
to grab something from, and then
$ ID just represents something
like 1, 2, 3, the ID of the
user that I want to get.
If the user is null, what's the
implication apparently, Isaac?
>> Well you do the
query all over again.
>> Okay good but in what case
would user be null do you think?
>> When they don't exist.
>> Good when they're not in
the cache, when user 1, 2,
3 or whoever I'm looking
for is not in the cache,
that variable is going to
be null and so we do this
IF condition as Isaac said,
and here there are
somewhat familiar code,
PDO which relates to
MySQL in our case.
We connect to the database
using that user and path,
we then execute the
query function in PDO,
in this case select star from
users where ID equals ID.
I'm not using my --
I'm not escaping ID
because in this case, I'm
assuming I know it's an integer
so it's not a dangerous
string just to be clear.
Then I'm calling fetch to
get back an associative array
of my data, the users
name, email address, ID,
whatever else I've
got in my database
but then the last thing I do
before apparently nothing else
because this is out of context,
before actually using that user
for anything, what
am I doing with him?
Axle?
>> You're storing it
in the caching memory.
>> Exactly I'm storing
a key value pair
in the cache whereby the key is
the user's ID, so this implies
that there's an ID field in
the user object that came back
from the database,
from this line here
and the value is the
user object itself.
So again a Memcache in this case
is a key value storage mechanism
and the next time I want to look
up this user, I want to look him
up by his ID and case in point,
that's what I did
in line 2 up top.
Now caches are finite
because RAM is finite
and even disk is finite, so
what could happen eventually
with my cache?
Just by nature of that --
those constraints, Axle?
>> It gets so big you can't
keep it on the machine.
>> Good so eventually
the cache could get
so big you can't it
keep on the machines,
so what would be a reasonable
thing to do at that point,
when you've run out of RAM
or disk space for cache?
You're the person implementing
Memcached itself now,
what do you do in that
case, you could just kind
of quit unexpected error
but would kind of be bad
and completely unnecessary.
What could you do?
Isaac?
[ Inaudible Speaker ]
I'm sorry.
>> Garbage collection.
>> Yeah so some kind
of garbage collection
and which things
would you collect?
What things would you
remove from memory?
[ Inaudible Speaker ]
Good, so we can essentially
expire objects based
on when they were put in.
So if I put in user
1, 2, 3 yesterday
and I haven't touched him
since or needed him since
and I need more space, well out
goes user 1, 2,3 and I can reuse
that space, that memory for
user 4, 5, 6 if user 4, 5,
6 is the next person I'm trying
to insert into the cache.
So indeed this is a very common
mechanism whereby the first one
is the first one out if
that object has not
been needed since.
By contrast if 1,
2, 3 is just one
of these power users who's
logging in quite a bit and he --
he or she is logging and
again, and again, and again,
well I should remember
every time
and we don't see it
in the code here.
But every time I get a cache hit
and I actually find user 1, 2,
3 in the cache, I could
somehow execute another Memcache
function that just touches
the user object so to speak.
Thereby updating his timestamp
to be this moment in time
so that you remember
that he was just selected
and hopefully Memcache
get itself would do
that for us and indeed it does.
I don't need to this manually,
the cache software
would remember, Oh,
you asked for user 1,
2, 3 I should move --
probably move him back
to the front of the line
so that the person at the
end of the line is first one
to get evicted next time around.
So it's a wonderfully
useful mechanism
and Facebook is very read heavy
or very write heavy
if you're a user.
It's kind of both these
days, you know earlier
on it was much more read
heavy than write heavy
because there were no
like status updates
and you would just have your
profile and that was about it.
So these days there's definitely
more writes but I'm going
to guess that reads are still
more common than not, right?
When you log -- if you're
a Facebook user and you log
into your accounts and you
see your newsfeed, you know,
you might have 10, 20
whatever friends show up in
that newsfeed, that's
potentially like 10
or 20 queries of some sort and
yet you 're probably not going
to update your status 30 times
at -- in that same unit of time.
So odds are Facebook is still
a little more read heavy
which makes caches is
all the more compelling
because if your own profile
isn't changing all that often
at least you might get 10 page
used, 100 page used by friends
or random strangers before you
actually update your status
or your profile again.
That's an opportunity for
optimization, so early on
and to this day, Facebook uses
things like Memcashe quite a bit
so that they're not hitting
their various databases just
to generate your profile.
They're instead just
getting the results
of some previous lookup
unless it has since expired.
Well onto my MySQL optimization
so that you can squeeze
all the more performance
out of your set up.
So this table's a little
more overwhelming right now
than it needs to be but
recall our discussion
about MySQL storage
engine some time ago.
And we talked briefly
about my ISAM and NODB;
does anyone remember
at least one
of the distinguishing
characteristics
of those two storage engines?
And again the storage engine was
just like the underline format
that was used to store
your database data.
>> I think NODB supported
transactions into [inaudible].
>> Good, so NODB which
is the default these days
so you haven't really
needed to think
about this much since
project one.
NODB supports transactions
whereas MyISAM does not.
MyISAM uses locks which are
full table locks but does tend
to have some other
properties and these --
this list here is
a very long list
of various distinctions among
these several storage engines.
Transactions is one of them
but there's a few other
storage engines here
that I thought I would
just draw our attention to.
So one, you have a memory
engine otherwise known
as a heap engine.
This is a table that's
intentionally only store in RAM
which means if you
lose power, server dies
or what not the entire contents
of these memory tables
will be lost.
But still kind of a nice
feature if you yourself want
to implement a cache relatively
easily by writing keys
and values into your database
and to two columns maybe,
you yourself can implement some
kind of cache to avoid having
to touch maybe much larger
tables that you yourself have.
So that's an option to you.
Archive Storage Engine, haven't
had to use this but take a guess
as to what it does besides
archiving something.
What does this engine do
for you, do you think?
>> It doesn't seem to
be doing very much,
it probably just
stores [inaudible].
>> And what -- what
was the last sentence,
the last part of your comment?
>> It doesn't store anything
in cache [inaudible].
>> Oh, it doesn't store
in anything in cache,
you have to query
it all the time.
Not quite.
So the property you're actually
getting and you can kind
of see it here, but
there's some footnotes
on the other storage engines,
is it's compressed by default.
So archive tables are
actually slower to query,
but they're automatically
compressed for you, so they take
up much, much less space.
So a common case
-- common use case
for archive tables might be
log files, where you want
to keep the data around and you
want to write out a whole bunch
of key values in a row.
Every time someone
hits your web server
or anytime something
buys someone,
but suppose you rarely query
that data, you're keeping it
for posterity, for
research purposes,
for diagnostic purposes,
but you're not going
to do any selects
on it anytime soon.
So it would just be
a waste to keep --
use more disk space than you
need to, so you're willing
to sacrifice some future
performance when you do need
to query it for some
long-term disk saving.
So, the archive format
allows you to do that.
NDB is a network storage engine,
which is used for clustering.
So that actually there is a
way of redressing the issue
of single points of failure
that we discussed earlier
with shared storage, but
we'll see a simpler approach
in just a moment.
So, in the world of
databases, like MySQL,
they typically offer
this replication feature
that I mentioned earlier.
So replication is all about
making automatic copies
of something and the terminology
generally goes as follows.
You generally have
a master database,
which is where you read
data from and write data to,
but just for good measure,
that master has one
or more slave databases attached
to it by a network connection,
and their purpose in life is
to get a copy of row that's
in the master database.
You can think of
it rather simply
as anytime a query is
executed on the master,
that same query is copied
down to one or more slaves
and they do the exact
same thing.
So that in theory, the master
in all of these slaves,
are identical to one another.
So what's the upside now of
having databases one, two,
three and four, all
of which are copies
of one another apparently?
What problems does this
solve for us, if any?
Axle?
>> Well, database one dies
because somebody trips
over the cord, but you
still have three copies.
>> Good, so if something --
if database one dies
because of human error,
you trip over the cord, hard
drive dies, RAM fizzles out,
whatever the case may be, you
have literally three backups
that are identical, so
there's no tapes involved,
there's no backup server.
I mean, these are
full-fledged databases
and in the simplest case, you
could just unplug the master,
plug in the slave and viola,
you now have a new master.
And you might have to do
a bit of reconfiguration
in the databases to make --
to promote him to master,
so to speak and then leave
servers three and four
as the new slaves while
you fix server number one.
But that would be
one approach here,
so you have some redundancy,
even though you might have
a little bit of downtime,
at least you can get back
up and running quickly.
And indeed, you can automate
this process if you notice
that the master is down,
you could take him offline
completely, promote the slave
and reconfigure them all
just by writing a script.
What else -- how else can we
take advantage of this topology?
Let me ask a more
leading question.
In the context of Facebook,
especially early days,
how might they in
particular have made good use
of this topology?
Axle?
>> Well, maybe if you get a
lot of the -- a lot of queries,
you can outsource them
to different slaves.
>> Okay, so if you're getting
a lot of queries, you could,
you know, maybe you
could just load balance
across database servers,
and absolutely you could.
The load balancers don't have
to be used for HDP alone.
You could use it
for MySQL traffic,
but why do I say
Facebook in particular?
Early on they didn't get
that many queries, but it --
this was still a good
paradigm for them.
[ Inaudible Speaker ]
Yeah, why is this good, perhaps?
So, back to my hypothesis
that they're more read
heavy than write heavy.
How can you adapt that --
that reality to this
particular topology effectively?
Or put another way, why is this
a good topology for a website
that is very read heavy
and less write heavy?
Ben?
[ Inaudible Speaker ]
Okay.
>> But if you're not
writing [inaudible].
>> Okay, good.
So reading can be expedited,
so if we kind of combine Ben
and Axles' proposals here,
for a read heavy website
like Facebook, certainly
in the early days,
you could just write
your code in such a way
that any select statements go
to databases two, three or four
and any inserts, updates or
deletes have to go apparently
to server one, which even though
that query than has to propagate
to servers two, three and
four, it is less common.
And that happens automatically,
so the code wise, you don't have
to worry about it too much
and if you're suffering a bit
of performance there, well you
can just throw more servers
at it and have even
more read servers
to lighten the load further.
So this approach
of having slaves
that can typically be used
either for redundancy,
so you just have a hot
spare ready to go or so
that you can balance
read requests
across them is a very nice
solution, but of course,
every time we solve one problem,
we've introduced another
or at least we haven't
fixed yet another here.
What is a -- what is a
fault in this layout still?
Be paranoid.
Kind of talked about it earlier,
but like what if
one dies, right?
Unless this is - there's got to
be some blip on the radar here
because we have to like
promote a slave and, right so,
you still have a single point
of failure here, at
least for writes.
We could keep Facebook alive by
letting people browse profiles
and read profiles, but
status updates for instance,
could be offline for
as long as it takes us
to promote a slave to a master.
Feels like it'd be nicer
or at least our probability
would be better of uptime
if we instead had not just
a single master, but again,
let's just throw
hardware at the problem.
So another common
paradigm is actually
to have a master-master setup
whereby as the labels imply
and as the arrows suggest,
this time you could write
to either server one or two,
and if you happen to write
to server one, that
query gets replicated
on server two and vice versa.
So now, you could
keep it simple.
You could always write to
one, but then the query goes
to number two automatically
or you could write to either,
thereby load balancing
across the two
and they'll propagate
between each other.
But in this case
here, if you've laid
out your network connections
properly, either one
or two can go down, and
you still have a master
that you could read from,
and you could even
implement this in code.
Recall very simply, we had the
MySQL connect function weeks
ago, or even the PDO
constructor function,
which tries to connect
to a database.
You can implement this in PHP
code if MySQL connect fails
when connecting to server
one, then just try server two.
So you yourself could
build in some redundancy
so that now we can lose
server one or two and not have
to intervene as humans
just yet because we
at least still have
a second master
that we can continue writing
to even though server one is now
offline for some amount of time.
All right, but we still
have to route traffic there,
so in pursuit of this
idea of load balancing,
here's a more complex picture
that starts to unite some
of our web ideas and some
of our database ideas.
So at the top there we
have some kind of network.
We have a load balancer
in between
and then we have
this front-end tier.
So web servers are typically
called a tier, a service tier,
this is a multi-tiered
architecture,
would be the jargon here.
And those web servers now
apparently are routing their
requests through what in order
to reach some MySQL
slaves for reads?
Who's the man in
the middle here?
Yeah, Axle?
>> For reads with
a load balancer.
>> Okay, so for reads, yeah,
we have a second load
balancer depicted here,
frankly in reality they
could be one in the same.
They could be the same
device, but just listening
for different types
of connections.
But for now, they're drawn
more simply as separate.
Now we have one MySQL
master, so we also have wires
or arrows pointing from the
web servers to the master.
And the master meanwhile,
has some kind
of connection to the slaves.
So not bad, no frankly, this
is starting to hurt my brain
because now what was
a very simple class
where you have a nice
self contained appliance
on your machine -- on your
laptop, does everything, web,
database, caching,
anything you want it to do.
My God, look at all the
things we have to wire up now
and it's still now perfect.
What could die here?
Where -- what are our
single points of failure?
Jack?
[ Inaudible Speaker ]
Oh, Isaac, sure.
>> All right, MySQL master.
>> Okay, so the MySQL master.
We haven't really solved that
problem, so kind of be nice
to steal part of
the previous picture
and maybe insert it into here.
Jack?
>> Oh, I was [inaudible].
>> Same thing.
Axle?
>> [Inaudible] load balancer.
>> Load balancers, right.
So single point of failure
is very well defined,
like single point of
failure, just look for any --
any bottlenecks here, whereby
things point in and then go out.
Load balancer is one here,
load balancer is one there,
so it turns out with load
balancers for your $100,000,
you can get two of them
typically in the package.
And what they tend to do is
operate also on what's called,
similar in spirit to
master-master mode,
but in the context
of load balancers,
it's typically called
active-active,
as opposed to active-passive.
And the idea here is with
active-active, you have a pair
of load balancers that
are constantly listening
for connections.
Either one of which can receive
packets from the outside world
and then relay them
to backend servers.
And what they typically do is
they send heartbeats from left
to right and right
to left so that
if this guy ever stops hearing
a heart beat from this guy,
so to speak and a heartbeat
is just like a packet
that gets sent every second
or something like that.
If this guy stops hearing
a heartbeat from this guy,
he automatically assumes that
this guy must have gone offline
so he's completely in charge now
and he continues to send traffic
from the outside world in,
or if you instead have
active-passive mode,
if this is the active
guy at the moment,
rather if this is the active
guy at the moment and he dies,
this guy similarly detects,
"Ooh, no more heartbeat."
And what the passive guy will
do is promote himself to active,
which essentially
just means he takes
over the other guys IP address
so that all traffic
now comes to him.
So in short, we definitely
need another load balancer
in the picture, how
it's implemented is --
is not as important
to us right now,
but having a single load
balancer is probably a bad
thing, right.
And this is the tragedy,
you can throw money at,
you can throw a lot of brain
power at various tiers here,
but if you have a lot of web
servers, a lot of MySQL servers,
but you have one
load balancer just
because it was really
expensive or you didn't know how
to configure it properly, like
the rest of it is pretty much
for naught because you still
have things that can die
and take down your
entire website.
So let's make this
more complex still.
So let's now introduce
two load balancers
and let's actually introduce
an idea of partitioning.
And this was actually something
that Facebook coincidentally
did make good use of early on.
Back in the day, there
was Harvard.facebook.
-- Harvard.thefacebook.com,
there was mit.thefacebook.com
and the earliest
partitioning that they used was
to essentially have
a different server,
as best outsiders could
tell for each school.
So they literally just
like copied the database,
copied the files over to
another server and then viola,
thus was born MIT's
copy of Facebook.
But this is actually, even
though this would get kind
of messy for 800 million users
and thousands and thousands
of universities and networks,
it's pretty clean early
on because it's just to leverage
this idea of partitioning,
right, it's kind of
-- we didn't have a --
Facebook didn't have a big
enough server to handle Harvard
and MIT, so why not just get two
and say Harvard users go here,
MIT users go here and now we've
kind of avoided that problem.
Now unfortunately, when BU comes
on, we need a third server,
but at least we can
scale horizontally.
Now there is a catch
with partitioning,
as soon as you wanted to be
able to poke someone at MIT
or vice versa, you
had to somehow cross
that Harvard/MIT boundary
at which point it's kind
of a bad thing that they're
all in separate databases.
So early on, there were some
features that you could only do
within your own network,
not until there was more share
state could you send messages
and the like.
So partitioning though could
be used even more simply.
Suppose that you just had
a whole bunch of users,
well you need to scale your
architecture horizontally,
why don't I just put users who's
last names start with a to m
on half of my servers and then n
through z on the others, right.
And when they log in,
I just send them to one
or the other server
based on that.
So in general, partitioning
is not such a bad idea,
it's very common in databases
because you can still
have redundancy,
whole bunch of slaves in this
case here, whole bunch of slaves
over here, but you
can balance load based
on some high level user
information, not based on load,
not round robin, you
can actually take
into account what someone's
name is and then send them
to this particular server.
So partitioning is a
very common paradigm.
And then lastly just
to slap a word on it,
high availability refers to
what we described in the context
of load balancers, but it can
apply to databases as well.
Whereby high availability or HA
is the buzzword, simply refers
to some kind of relationship
between a pair or more
of servers that are somehow
checking each other's
heartbeats, so that if one
of them dies, the other takes
on the entire burden of the --
of the service that's being
provided, whether a database
or whether a load balancer.
So, even though we finally
got the iPad working,
it's a little small to draw
on, so what I wanted to do
as our final example here,
is let me raise the
screen here [inaudible] one
of these buttons will do it.
All right, we're
going old school now.
Our first and last piece of
chalk in the class, let's see.
We'll start with the middle one.
All right, let's build
ourselves a network here.
So, we have a need for
one or more web servers,
one or more databases,
maybe some load balancers,
but we're also going to try
to tie together last week's
conversation about security,
so we'll have to think about
firewalling things out now.
So in very simple form,
we have here a web server,
which I'll draw as www.
All right, so that's
our web server.
And now my website's
doing so well
that I need a second web
server, so I'm going to draw it
like this and now we need
to revisit the issue
of balancing load.
So what felt like one of
our best options here?
How do I still have the
internet, which I'll draw
as a cloud here, connected to
both of these servers somehow,
but I want the property
of sticky sessions.
So what are my options or
what was my best option?
How do I implement
sticky sessions?
Axle?
>> Use a load balancer and keep
all the sessions [inaudible].
>> Okay, good.
So use a load balancer and store
all the sessions in one place.
And that's not -- okay,
so we can actually do one,
but not necessarily
both of those.
Let me interpose now the thing
we started calling black box.
So this is some kind
load balancer,
now I still have
my backend servers.
And here's another one here.
Okay. And now this
is connected here,
but I still want sticky
sessions, but you know what?
Shared states, that
sounded expensive,
fiber channel [inaudible]
sounded complicated,
there's simpler way.
How do I ensure that I get
sticky sessions using only a
load balancer and
no shared state yet?
How can I ensure that when
Alice comes in and she's sent
to this server the first time,
that the next time she comes in,
she's sent to the same one?
Axle?
>> Remember which server she
visits either for [inaudible].
>> Okay, good.
So why don't we have the load
balancer listen at the HDP level
and when the response comes
back from the first web server,
let's give them numbers.
So let's call this one,
and this guy two --
the load balancer can
insert some kind of cookie
that allows it to remember that
this user belongs on server one.
And how it does that, I don't
know, it's a big random number
and it's got a table like
PHP does for its sessions
and figures out which server
to send her to in this case.
All right, so now
I have a database.
The easiest way I know how to
set up a database is to put it
on the web server itself.
So much like the CS50
appliance, you have a database
in the same box as a web server.
If I now have a database here
and here on the same boxes
as our web servers, what's
the most obvious problem
that now arises?
Yeah?
>> Well, Alice's
shopping cart is --
oh, well if she does something
to her profile or whatever --
>> Good.
>> -- it's just going to be on
server one and not on server two
since she just visited
server one.
>> Exactly.
So if Alice just happens
to end up on server one
and she updates her profile,
her credit card information
or something persistent.
Not the shopping cart thing
because that involves
the session,
but she does something
persistent,
it's going to persist on
this database and that's fine
because sticky sessions are
solving all my problems now.
But she comes back
in a week or she logs
in from a different computer,
cookie expires, whatever,
and she ends up here --
what happened to my
credit card information?
What happened to my profile?
I now have no profile because
I'm on a different database.
So clearly, this is not going
to fly unless we
partition our users
and have the load balancer
actually take into account
who is this user and
then send the user based
on Alice's last name
always to the same servers,
so that could be one approach.
But for now, let's instead
factor out the database and say
that it's not on the web
servers, it's separate
and it's got some kind of
internet connection here.
Of course we've solved
one problem,
but introduced a new
one, which is what?
Isaac?
>> Single point of
failure [inaudible].
>> Yeah. So single
point of failure again.
So how can we mitigate this?
Well, we can do a
couple of things.
We can attach slave
databases off of this,
and that's kind of nice.
But it then involves
somehow promoting a slave
to a master in the
even one dies.
So maybe the cleanest
approach would be something
like two master databases,
so we'll call this
db1, this will be db2.
And now, how do I want to do
this, connect these like this.
Isaac, you shook your head.
>> Well, you could connect the
two databases to each other.
>> Okay, so we should
probably do this
for master-master replication.
So that's good.
But what about these
lines -- good, bad?
Answer is bad.
Why bad, Jack?
>> Well, you can connect each
one to both of the [inaudible].
>> Right, so the problem we
just identified was the database
on same server is web server bad
because then it's talking only
to it and if Alice ends
up on the other servers,
she has no data that
you're expecting.
Well, functionally
this is equivalent.
I've just drawn a line, but
they're still only connected
to each other and the
traffic should probably not go
like that, so we at least need
to have some kind
of cross connect.
So okay, so I can do this,
but now what do I do?
So now my load balancing
has to be done in code,
if those are the only components
in my systems right now,
the line suggests that dub, dub,
dub one has a network connection
to db1 and db2, but that means
now I have to do something
like an if condition only
in my PHP code to say
if this database
is up right here,
else if this database
is up right there.
And that's not bad, but
now you're developers have
to know something
about the topology.
If you ever introduce a third
master or something like that,
although MySQL though
wouldn't play nicely with that,
now you have to change
your code.
This is not a nice
layer of abstraction,
so how else could
we solve this, Axle?
I don't like the idea
of connecting each
of my web servers to the
database because frankly,
you know what, this is
going to get really ugly
if it starts looking
like this, right.
Very quickly this
degrades into a mess.
Yeah?
>> Get another machine,
load balancer [inaudible].
>> Okay, good.
>> [Inaudible] all of
that, so connect your --
your dub, dub, dub
servers to a load balancer,
then let it handle the request.
And then you can implement all
kinds of features like say,
they are both masters, right?
>> Uh-huh.
>> They have the same data.
>> What if only users with last
name that starts with M logs in,
well, you're going to have a
load on one particular server,
but then the load balancer
can take all those features we
talked about --
>> Good.
>> -- CPU cycles
and all of that,
and actually distribute MySQL
queries across databases.
>> Okay, good.
So we insert a load balancer
here, which is connected
to both the dub,
dub, dub machines
and also the database servers.
And then he can be
responsible for load balancing
across the two masters.
It's actually harder for
the database to do any kind
of intelligence load
balancing based on last names
at this point, since the MySQL
traffic is going to operate
with binary messages, not with
http style textual messages.
The load balancer up here
can look at HDP headers
and make intelligent decisions.
It's harder, maybe
not impossible,
but it wouldn't be very common
to do load balancing based
on application layer
intelligence here.
You would probably push that to
the PHP code again in that case.
But this isn't bad,
but Isaac doesn't
like this picture
now because of what?
>> It still fails [inaudible].
>> Yeah, so we still have
the single point of failure,
so you just cost me even more
money or more complexity,
even if I'm using free software.
This just takes more time now.
So now we have load balancer
one, load balancer two,
I need to do something
like this.
And even though this looks
a little ridiculous, well,
actually it's a little elegant.
That's pretty sexy.
So, you would do this
with switches or some kind
of Ethernet cables all going
into some central source.
So suppose instead
we actually did that?
If you've ever plugged in a
computer into a network jack,
which most of you probably
have even if you have a laptop,
you don't connect these
computers all to themselves.
You instead connect them to
like a big switch that has lots
of Ethernet ports that
you can plug into.
But now Isaac, what -- what do
you not like about this idea
if I'm plugging everything
into a switch?
>> It still fails.
>> Yeah, so welcome to the world
of like, network redundancy.
So really the right way to do
this is to have two switches,
so almost everyone of your
servers, database and web alike,
as well as you load
balancers, would typically have
at least two Ethernet
jacks in them.
And one cable would
go to one switch,
and another cable would
go to the other switch.
You have to be super careful not
to create loops of some sort.
So switches have to be
somewhat intelligent typically
so that you don't
create this crazy mess
where traffic is just
bouncing and bouncing
around in your internal network
and nothing's getting in or out.
So there's -- there's some
care that has to be taken,
but in general, this is
really the theme in ensuring
that you have not only
scalability, but redundancy
and higher probabilities
of uptime
and resilience against failure.
You really do start
cross connecting many
different things.
But let's push harder.
Isaac, what -- suppose
I fix the switch issue,
suppose I also make
this two load balancers
and fix that issue.
What's something else
that could fail now?
Can't do this on
an iPad very well.
So, this is your datacenter.
Here is the door
to your datacenter.
Jack?
>> The building burns down.
>> [Inaudible] good, more
extreme that I had in mind.
I was thinking the power
goes out, but that works too.
So the building itself
burns down or goes offline.
You have some kind of
network disconnect between you
and your ISP, the whole building
or the power indeed does go out.
And this has happened.
In fact, one of the things
that happens every
time Amazon goes out,
is the whole world
starts to think
that Cloud's cloud computing,
so to speak, is a -- the --
a bad thing because,
"Oh, my God.
Look, you can't keep
the cloud up."
But the tragedy here
is in this perception,
that cloud computing really
just refers to outsourcing
of services and sharing
resources like power
and networking and
security and so forth
across multiple customers.
So Amazon services EC2,
elastic compute cloud,
is kind of this picture here
whereby you don't own the
servers, but you do
rent space on them,
because they give
you VPSes that happen
to be housed inside
of this building.
Amazon offers things
called availability zones,
whereby this might be an
availability zone called US East
one, so this is a
building in Virginia,
in that particular case.
And what they offer though is
US East two and three and four,
though they call them A
and B and C and D. And what
that simply means in theory is
that there's another building
like this, drawn over there
that does not share
the same power source,
does not share the
same networking cables.
And so, even if something
goes wrong in one building,
in theory the other
shouldn't be affected.
However, Amazon has
suffered outages
in multiple availability
zones, multiple datacenters,
so in addition to having
servers in Virginia,
guess where else
they have servers?
>> Anywhere else.
>> Okay, anywhere else, Yeah,
that's actually a
pretty hard question,
the world's a big place.
So the West Coast and in
Asia, and in South America
and in Europe, as well.
They have different regions
as they call them inside
of which are different
datacenters
or availability zones.
But this just means that you
can really drive yourself crazy
thinking through all the
possible failure scenarios,
because even though
Jack's building burning
down is a little extreme, things
like that do happen, right.
If you have a massive storm,
like a tornado or a hurricane
that just knocks out power,
absolutely could a whole
building goes down -- go down.
So what do you do in that case?
Well, we have to have a second
datacenter or availability zone.
I'll draw it much
smaller this time,
even though it might be
this -- physically the same.
So here's another one.
Suppose that inside of
this building is exactly
that same topology,
so now really what we have is
the internet outside these boxes
connecting to both buildings.
So -- so internet is no
longer inside the building.
So, once you have
two datacenters,
how do you now distribute your
load across two datacenters?
Axle?
>> Well, then you can
use the DNS [inaudible].
>> Yeah, so we -- we didn't
really spend much time on it,
but recall that you can do load
balancing at the DNS level.
And this is indeed how you can
do geography based geolocate --
geography based load balancing,
whereby now when someone
on the internet requests the
IP address of something.com,
they might get the IP address
really of this building
or more specifically, of the
load balancer in this building.
Or they might get the IP
address of load balancer
in this building, right.
When we did the [inaudible]
lookup on Google,
we got a whole bunch of results.
That's not because they
have one building with lots
of load balancers inside of it.
That's because they probably
have lots of separate buildings
or datacenters, different
countries even,
that themselves have
different entry points,
different IP addresses.
So you have global
load balancing,
as it's typically called.
Then the request
comes into a building,
and you still have the
issue of somehow making sure
that subsequent traffic
gets to the same place,
because odds are Google is
not sharing your session
across entirely -- entirely
different continents.
Even though, they could be,
but that would probably be
expensive or slow to do.
So odds are you're going to stay
in that building for some amount
of time, but again, these
ideas we've been talking
about just get magnified
the bigger
and bigger you start to think.
And even then, you
have potential downtime
because if a whole building
goes offline and your browser
or your computer happens
to of cached the IP address
of that building,
that datacenter,
could take some minutes or some
hours for your TTL to expire
at which point you get
rerouted to something else.
Not too long ago,
just a few weeks,
I think Core [phonetic]
was offline
for several hours one
night because they Amazon.
A bunch of other
popular websites too,
who use Amazon services
were down altogether
because they were in a
building or a set of buildings
that suffered this
kind of downtime.
And it's hard.
Like if you are having
the fortunate problem
of way too many users and lots
of revenue, it gets harder
and harder to actually
scale things out globally.
So, typically people
do what they can,
but Isaac has gotten very
good at pointing out,
you can at least avoid as
best as possible these kinds
of single points of failure.
Questions?
So a word on security then.
Let's focus only
on this picture,
not so much on the building.
What kind of traffic now
needs to be allowed in
and out of the building?
So let me go ahead and just
give myself some internet here,
connecting to the load
balancers somehow.
What type of internet
traffic should be coming
from the outside world in
if I'm hosting a website,
a LAMP based website?
Yeah?
>> Well, you would
want a firewall
that allows only
port 80 connections.
>> Okay, good.
So I want TCP, recall
which is one
of the transport
protocols 80 on the way in.
That's good, but you just
compromised by ability
to have certain security, why?
You're not blocking a very
useful type of traffic.
>> Oh, yeah, the
encrypted [inaudible].
>> Good, so we also want 443 --
>> Yeah.
>> -- which is the default
port that's used for SSL,
for HTTPS based URL's.
So that's good.
This means now that the
only traffic allowed
into my datacenter
is TCCP80 and 443.
Now those familiar with SSH,
you've also just locked yourself
out of your datacenter,
because you cannot now SSH
into your datacenter, you
might want to allow something
like port 22, for
SSH or you might want
to have an SSL based VPN so
that you can connect somehow
to your datacenter remotely.
And again, it doesn't
have to be a datacenter,
this can just be some webhosting
or some VPS hosting
company that you're using.
And okay, so we might need one
or more other ports for our VPN,
but for now that's pretty good.
How about the load balancers?
What kind of traffic needs to go
from the load balancer
to my web servers?
Well, it -- it's really a
mess to keep it encrypted
because once it's inside the
datacenter, nobody else is going
to listen [inaudible] people
inside the datacenter.
>> Okay.
>> So you would want to drop
the encryption and do 80.
>> Good, and that's actually
very common to offload your SSL
to the load balancer
or some special device
and then keep everything
else unencrypted
because if you control
this, it's at least safer.
Not 100%, because if
someone compromises this now,
they're going to see
your traffic unencrypted.
But if you're okay with that,
doing the SSL termination here,
so everything's encrypted from
the internet down to here,
but then everything else goes
over normal unencrypted http.
The upside of that is remember
the whole certificate thing?
You don't need to put your
SSL certificate on all
of your web servers, you can
just put it in the load balancer
or the load balancers.
You can get expensive
load balancers
to handle the cryptography and
the computational cost thereof.
You can get cheaper web servers
because they don't need to worry
as much about that
kind of overhead.
So that's one option.
So TCP 80 here and here.
How about the traffic
between the web server
and the databases, perhaps
through these load balancers?
This is a more of
a trivia question.
But what kind of -- what
kind of traffic is it,
even if you don't
know the port number?
Yeah?
>> It's a -- it's
query or execute.
>> Yeah, query actually
-- or more specifically,
it's the SQL queries
like select and insert
and delete and so forth.
So this is generally TCP
3306, which is the port number
that MySQL uses by default.
So what does this mean?
If you do have firewalling
capabilities
and we haven't drawn any
firewalls per say, so we do need
to insert some hardware into
this picture that would allow us
to actually make these kinds
of configuration changes,
but if we assume we have
that ability in large part
because all of these things
are plugged in as we said
to some kind of switch, well
the switch could be a firewall
itself and we could make
these configuration changes.
We can further lock
things down, why?
I mean, everything just works
if I don't firewall things.
Why would I want to
bother tightening things
so that only 80 and
443 are allowed here,
and 3306 is allowed here?
And in fact, notice there's
no line between these guys.
>> Well, it would be really
stupid to keep, for example,
3306 open in the first
firewall because then people --
they might not be
able to because
of other security measures,
but in theory, they --
they are allowed by the firewall
to query your database
and do SQL commands.
>> Good, exactly.
There's just no need
for people to be able
to potentially even execute
SQL queries coming in
or make MySQL connections.
And even if you're not even
listening for MySQL connections,
it again is sort of the
principle of the thing.
You should really have the --
the principle of least privilege
whereby you only open those
doors that people actually
have to go through,
otherwise you're just
inviting unexpected behavior
because you left the
door ajar, so to speak.
You left the port open and it's
not clear whether someone might
in fact, take advantage of that.
Case and point, if somehow you
screw up or Apache screws up
or PHP screws up, and this
server is compromised,
it'd be kind of nice if the only
thing this server can do is talk
via MySQL to this server
and cannot for instance,
suddenly SSH to this
server or poke around
or execute any commands on
your network other than MySQL.
So at least if the bad guy
takes this machine over,
you really can't leave this
rectangle here that I've drawn.
So again, beyond the scope of
things we've done in the class,
and even though the appliance
itself actually does have a
firewall that allows
certain ports in and out,
all of the ones you need, we
haven't had to fine tune it
for any of the projects,
realize that you --
that even on something like a
LINUX based operating system.
So in short, as soon as
you have the happy problem
of having way too many
users for your own good,
lots of new problems arise
even though thus far be focused
pretty much entirely on the
software side of things.
So that is it for
computer science S75.
I'll stick around for
questions one on one.
We still have a final section
tonight, for those of you
who would like to dive
into some related topics,
otherwise realize that
the final project two,
it's deadline is coming up.
You should've gotten
feedback by --
from your TF's about
project one,
if not just drop him
or her a note or me.
Otherwise, it's been a pleasure
having everyone in the class.
We will see you online
after tonight [applause].
Oh, that's okay.
Thanks, I wasn't trying to
build up to that there, sorry.